<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Answeres to certaine novations desired by some to be embraced by the reformed church some defend one part, others another part of these novations : in this treatise their chief objections are turned into questions.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 664.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1042</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19993220</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19993220</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23592</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20215)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23592)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1719:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Answeres to certaine novations desired by some to be embraced by the reformed church some defend one part, others another part of these novations : in this treatise their chief objections are turned into questions.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>72, [24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Holland :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D8 E4, 2A8 2B4.</note>
                  <note>Page 21 misnumbered as 23.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through and stained with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Christ Church (University of Oxford). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reformed Church --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23592:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23592:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Anſweres to certaine Novations <hi>deſired by ſome to be embraced by</hi> the reformed Church: Some defend one <hi>part, others another part of theſe nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> In this treatiſe their chief obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions <hi>are turned into Queſtions.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 9. verſe 26.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall be aſhamed of me, and of my words, of him ſhall the Son of man bee aſhamed, when he ſhall come in his glory, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Cornelis Lodewijcksz van der Plasse</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <q>HET HUYS OP EEN STEEN<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ROTZ GHEGRONT SCHAEDT GEEN PLASRE<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>GEN OP STARCKEN WINT</q>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:23592:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAP. 1. <hi>Againſt uſurping privie meeting and night meetings.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 2. <hi>Some forbid maſters of families to interpret any Scriptures to their domeſticks.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 3. <hi>Some forbid all ſet formes of prayer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 4. <hi>Some forbid read prayers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 5. <hi>Some interrapt Gods worſhip, reading lines at the ſinging of pſalmes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 6. <hi>Some never ſing the words, Glorie to the Father, &amp;c. Others ſing them at all times.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 7. <hi>Some after divine ſervice bleſſe the people in a legall manner.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 8. <hi>Others reject presbyteriall government.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 9. <hi>The baptiſme of children before their years of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion forbidden.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 10. <hi>They deny that Miniſters admitted by biſhops arc lawfully called.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 11. <hi>Some forbid to converſe or ſerve God, where in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels or ignorant people are preſent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 12. <hi>They forbid preachers to read the works of learned men, for understanding Gods word.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 13. <hi>Publict reading of Scriptures, without interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, forbidden.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 14. <hi>The office of Readers diſſallowed by ſome.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 15. <hi>They forbid private prayers of preachers in the pulpit, before publict ſervice; and they forbid all private prayers of people in Churches.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. 16. <hi>The principall opinions of Antinomians or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:23592:2"/>
               <head>CHAPTER 1. Againſt uſurping privie meetings, for exerciſing <hi>miniſteriall dueties, pretending mutuall</hi> edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: as alſo of night meetings.</head>
               <p>Queſtion <hi>MAY we not at all times, and in all places convocat people for mutuall edification, not ſeeking libertie of their Pastours, as did the apoſtles and diſciples?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not only men not called to preach, but alſo Paſtours and Preachers may not doe it. 2. The apoſtles and diſciples might lawfully preach publickly &amp; privatly in all places, without uſurpation, for none other had the miniſterial charge but themſelves. 3. Preachers law fully called by men firſt teaching true doctrine, and afterwards they turne apoſtats or hereticks; thereby they loſſe the right of a lawfull calling, for GOD ſendeth none to teach errors and hereſies, and men have no warrand of GOD to call them. Theſe apoſtats and hereticks are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come uſurpers of the places whereunto they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and therefore ſound teachers may convocat privie meetings in theſe paroches without their warrand, and without uſurpation. But it is uſurpation to do ſo in the paroches of ſound teachers. 4. <hi>Paul</hi> forbad <hi>Timothie</hi> to lay hands upon any ſuddenly and that hee ſhould not be partakers of their ſins, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. Women may not ſpeak publictly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. They may teach younger wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men privatly, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.3. and they who admit men untry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unqualified, and without impoſition of hands, are partakers of all their ſins, he reſies and abuſes, which they bring into GODS church. 5. The apoſtles themſelves
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:23592:3"/>might not preach in any place uncalled. The Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad them to go to the Gentiles, and to the cities of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, and bade them go to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. But after his reſurrection he ſent them to all nations, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>Paul</hi> (<hi>Act.</hi> 20) biddeth Paſtours take heed, not to other mens flocks, but over which the holy Ghoſt made them overſeers. The Spirit ſuffered not <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothie</hi> to preach in <hi>Bithynia</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> but in <hi>Macedonia, Act.</hi> 16.6. Many pretend private meetings, but they plead for publict meetings under this name.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How are they publict?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In reſpect of perſons, place, and manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe. 1. The perſons are not of one familie only, nor two or three of ſundrie families, meeting occaſionally, but oftimes many families, and perſons of diverſe families towns and pariſhes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> their number exceeding ſundrie pariſhes. 2. The place though it be a chamber, or houſe ordained for private uſes, yet they make them publict houſes, appointing them for ordinarie publict meetings and publict exerciſes: Churches are for no other reſpects made publict houſes. 3. The exerciſes are publictin their uſage: for they doe not every two and two, or two and three, or three and three confer privatly together, but one ſpeaketh to all the reſt, and oftimes many ſpeake one after another: So theſe meetings are more publict then ours, where only one or two ſpeak publictly.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Can the privie meetings of two or three uſurpe the ministeriall charge? Anſ.</hi> Two or three may uſurp over the dignitie and office of kings, as really as two or three thouſand, though the uſupation of a greater number be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:23592:3"/>more notable. If they appoint one of their number con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, or every one their time about to be king over the reſt, preſcribing and executing lawes, and receiving royall honour and obedience from the reſt, not being deputed by the lawfull king to that effect, it is uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13. ſaith, <hi>There is no power but that which is ordeined of God:</hi> yet without uſurpation we may admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and counſell one another to do all civile dueties. Such uſurpation may be in every juriſdiction of princes, rulers and magiſtrats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So in the eccleſiaſticall juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, if two or three eſtabliſh an ordinarie cuſtome of preaching, and of doing miniſteriall dueties, whether one alone, or every one their time about do the charge; they not being deputed, nor warranted by the ordinarie pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, it is uſurpation. In a well ordered citie the citizens ſuffer none to encroach upon their callings, liberties, and priviledges: much leſſe ſhould ſuch abuſes be tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat in a well ordered church. 2. Paſtors may preach both privatly and publictly in their own pariſhes. If in their infirmitie, abſence, or lawfull diſtractions, they imploy others in their places, it is a lawfull calling. 3. Men may teach their own families, it is warranted by GOD, though like <hi>Abrahams</hi> familie, 318. ſouls dwell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 4. All other meetings ſhould be occaſionall, not hindering familie worſhip, not ordinarie publict wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, nor the dueties of ſervants to their maſters, of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to their parents, and wives to their huſbands.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What meetings are occaſionall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such as are not of ſet purpoſe appointe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for ordinarie miniſteriall exerciſes, but when by the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:23592:4"/>of GOD men meet for other occaſions, either ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile or eccleſiaſticall, as 1. when two or three together take occaſion of the publict preachings in the Sabboth, to repeat the things they have heard: 2. They may edifie one another going together unto churches. 3. Within the churches, before the publict exerciſes begin, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween preachings, and when they are ended 4. At the preaching men may ſtir up one another unto attendance by example and exhortation: 5. Returning home they may uſe conference. 6. Walking or ſitting in the fields. 7. Meeting two or three together at markets or publict places. 8. Eating or drinking together. 9. In buying or ſelling together their ſpeaches and purpoſes ſhould ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of holineſſe, and of a godly converſation, and of a good conſcience. 10 Labouring together in a calling, and in all honeſt exerciſes 11. Going to wars together, 12. In doubtſome matters enquire at their paſtors, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learned men, 13. At publict catechiſing men may learne, hearing the anſwers, alſo the preachers ſhould cauſe ſome rehearſe conceived and ſet formes of prayer, that others may learn to pray, and ſchoolmaſters ſhould do ſo to their diſciples 14. And by miſſive letters, as the Saints did edifie one another in the primitive church. 15. And ſailing together. 16. Ryding or travelling on jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes. 17. Meeting at burials. 18. At extraordinarie feaſts. 19. At familie worſhip catechiſe them, teach them to pray, interpret obſcure paſſages of Scriptures, take an account what they have heard at publict preachings. If any occaſionally come in, he may hear theſe exerciſes. 20. Viſiting the ſick, the father leſſe, the priſoner, the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:23592:4"/>21. Viſiting friends and acquaintance. 22. By a godly life &amp; converſation, good example edifieth dayly.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Do not the Scriptures warrand us to meet ordinarly, for miniſteriall exerciſes and mutuall edification, as Hebr.</hi> 3.12 Exhort one another, while it is called to day. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.25. Let us conſider one another, not forſaking the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of our ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is, exhorting one another, <hi>&amp;c Pet.</hi> 4.10. As every man hath received, even ſo miniſter the ſame one to another. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.14. Warne them that are unruly, comfort the feeble minded, ſupport the weak. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.16. Let the Word of GOD dwell in you richly, in all wiſdome, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and admoniſhing one another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Such places perſwade mutuall edification, which may ſufficiently be done at the foreſaid occaſions: but no ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturs do warrand the uſurping meetings: GODS word ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther terrifieth from ſuch uſurpation and boldneſſe, as is ſeene in <hi>Vzza,</hi> ſmitten to death for touching the ark, and king <hi>Vzzia</hi> ſmitten with leproſie for offering incenſe. The earth ſwallowed up <hi>Korab</hi> and his companie, which were Levits, for ſeeking the Prieſthood, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. The ſons of <hi>Scaeva</hi> were wounded by one poſſeſſed with a devill, for uſurping the apoſtolick charge: theſe offices were good, but the perſons were not called. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſent of GOD to <hi>Pharao,</hi> fearing his own weakneſſe, deſired the LORD to ſend another: But now men, neither ſent of GOD, nor fearing their weakneſſe, uſurp the charges of others. 2. In <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.25. the apoſtle forbidding to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the aſſembires, ſpeaketh not of uſurping meetings-but of meetings where the apoſtles and preachers law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:23592:5"/>called were preſent, wherein the people exhorted one another to obſerve and practiſe ſuch things as were preached; and the People asked reſolutions of their doubts from the Preachers: As, <hi>What ſhall we doe to bee ſaved? Are they many that ſhall be ſaved? How often ſhall I forgive my brother, unto ſeven times? What ſhall bee the ſignes of thy coming, and of the end of the world Declare unto us this parable,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Math.</hi> 18. and 24. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. &amp;c. yea of times men did forſake the aſſemblies where <hi>Chriſt</hi> preached.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>God giveth not men talents to be hid up, but to be uſefull to others. Ergo men ſhould aſſemble for exerciſing their gifts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Doubtleſſe <hi>Korab,</hi> and the foreſaid uſurpers had gifts which they could make uſe of, but they had not a calling a. Men wanting a particular calling, may ſufficiently uſe all their gifts in their generall calling, and Chriſtian converſation, at ſuch occaſions as are fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned. 3. Becauſe ſome can govern a kingdome, ſhall they therefore take to themſelves royall juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and government. 4. Gifts are not hid up, if men be willing to uſe them, as GOD offereth occaſion: if no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion be offered, thy readie and willing intenſion excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee: thy gifts are not idle, if thou gaine thine own ſoul by them.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>The gifts of every member ſhould redound to the whole my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall bodie of Christ, Therefore wee ſhould convocat many to be partakers of our gifts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A hurt finger diſquieteth the whole bodie: if it bee cured the whole bodie is eaſed; ſo he that doeth good by one member of CHRIST, doth it to all: yea CHRIST eſte emeth it done to himſelfe.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:23592:5"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Should wee not edifie mutually, ſeeing it is ſaid in Zacharie,</hi> 8.21. <hi>The inhabitants of one citic ſhall go to another, ſaying, Let us go ſpeedily to pray before the Lord of Hostes, and I will goe alſo, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Are theſe either private or uſurping meetings, when they go openly to worſhip in the temple, as GODS people did yearly at the three great feaſts: So do the people of ſundrie townes in diverſe kingdomes go together into one church. 2. Is mutuall edification hindered, when thou art forbidden to doe it in an uſurping way, having lawfull occaſion beſide: you may thus ſay, Wee hinder you to live, becauſe we forbid you to live on roberie and thift, having ſufficient lawfull meanes beſide.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of night Meetings.</head>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>MAY wee not meet for mutuall edification in the night time, ſeeing the Apoſtles practiſed it. Act.</hi> 12. <hi>When Peter came to the houſe of Marie, and Act.</hi> 20. <hi>Paul preached untill midnight.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anſw. Vſurping meetings are neither lawfull day nor might. 2. In time of perſecution, and when Gods church was not in a ſetled eſtate, the Apoſtles and Diſciples might lawfully meet privily and publictly, both day and night, without uſurpation, for none had the charges but themſelves. At that time it was extraordinarie that people heard any preaching at all; therefore they ſpent both the day and the night in hearing, not knowing of the like occaſion againe. Paul preached never ſo long at Troas before nor after, and hee departed on the morrow. The people conveened occaſionally at the houſe of Marie, becauſe of the preſent perſecution, to exhort one another unto courage and conſtancie, and to pray for the deliverance of Peter, and other perſecuted Saints. 3. You have dayly occaſions of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict preaching, <hi>Varitas non quierit angulos,</hi> the Truth and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors thereof ſeek not to bee imployed in corners and ſecret places, if they can finde commodious publict places, though perſecution may chaſſe them unto ſecret places: But you affect
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:23592:6"/>ſecret places, when you haue ſuficient publict, it bewrayeth that your novations agree not with the truth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quest. What offenſes are effected by the uſurping privìe meetings?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anſ. They have no warrand of God, but the charge of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie publict and privie meetings, for religious exerciſes are committed to ordinarie Paſtors, and familie exerciſe to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of families, or their deputees. The Lord ſaid, Math. 10. <hi>That which I tell you ſecretly, proclaime you on thee houſ tops.</hi> Many things are more lawfully done in perſecution, and apoſtacie, and in the beginning of a church, then afterwards in time of peace and libertie. 2. They bewray ſome unwarranded exerciſes, and though the exerciſes be lawfull in themſelves, yet this ſecret u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of them in time of libertie ſhameth them, as if they were works of darkneſſe: the enemies of the truth have a fit occaſion ſo to judge of them, and to ſlander the profeſſion. 3. The fruits of privat meetings, which they call mutuall edification, are not greater knowledge of Gods word, and more devotion, and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life, then all theſe who are content of the lawfull ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie meetings, but they are greater oſtentation of theſe things, and the contempt of ſuch as follow not their courſes; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of ſundrie religious exerciſes, allowed by God in his word as ſet formes of prayer privat prayer in the pulpet, and in publict places, &amp;c. They ſpread abroad erroneous novations, people forſake their own paſtours, who preach againſt theſe novations, leaving their churches almoſt emptie, and they follow other preachers who countenance their errors; they ſo diſgrace the Miniſtrie, that their travels can do little or no good to their own flocks. 4. Thus they diſgrace the ordinarie publict meetings, as if they were but ciphers, and unprofitable for edification; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they cauſe a ſchiſme, but they are called ſchiſmaticks who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to be ſchiſmaticks. 5. They skar pagans and hereticks from converſion, who think that they meet for ſome lewdneſſe and filthineſſe, which they dare not do openly. 6. Hereticks at ſuch meetings (the Goſpel having libertie) wont to ſpread abroad their hereſies; who could cenſure them? for none knew what they taught, untill that ſo many were infected, that their errours could be no longer kept ſecret, and then they profeſſed them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly. 7. The papiſts in Scotland did meet privatly for idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:23592:6"/>worſhip, whereby they made way for the power of prelars that they began to obtrud their traditions publictly. 8. Though the braſen ſerpent was a divine ordinance, yet when they became a mean of diſhonouring God, and of ſpirituall hurt to the people it was deſtroyed: So though privie meetings were tolerable in time of apoſtaſie, yet when they now bring forth ſuch bitter fruits, they ſhould be aboliſhed. 9. The <hi>Patriark,</hi> themſelves were prieſts, untill that the Leviticall order was eſtabliſhed, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards king Uzzia was puniſhed for offering incenſe. Bezaleel &amp; A holiab might touch the ark, and look into it, when they were making the veſſels of the tabernacle, but after the conſecration of theſe things they might not touch them, nor look into the ark no more then Uzza and the Bethſhemits. So it is uſurpation to uſe ſuch meetings, when a lawfull publict order is eſtabliſhed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt. If the generall aſſemblie est abliſh ſuch meetings, can they be hurtfull?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anſ. If the kings and people of Iſrael had eſtabliſhed a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, that the people might chooſe rulers and judges over the whole kingdome, whenſoever they pleaſed, nevertheleſſe that they had kings. If much treaſon and uſurpation was committed when the king only rules, much more ſhould be committed by the multitude of rulers: So when the publict miniſtrie is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, before the eſtabliſhing of ſuch meetings, much more ſhould it bee after all ſhould be in confuſion; neither civile nor ſpirituall rulers ſhould keep people in order. 2. If a Lord ſend for ſome unruly ſervants to do ſome ſervice, they come to him paſſing through their neighbours ſtanding corn, though many plain paſſages bee beſides: if any reprove them for treading the corn, they accuſe the reprovers as enemies to their Lord, &amp; to his ſervice, becauſe they are forbidden to go to him in an unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; backward way and they prove that their Lord bad them come that way only, becauſe he bad them come to him: So the defenders of privie meetings accuſe their brethren as enemies to mutuall edification, becauſe they forbid them to do it in an uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping way, having ſufficient lawfull occaſons beſide: they prove that they ſhould doe that dutie in an uſurping way, only becauſe Gods word biddeth them do that duetie. 3. Salomon ſayeth, <hi>Thoverb.</hi> 9 <hi>Stollan waters are ſweet, and bread eaten in ſecret is pleaſant:</hi> So ſecret meetings a ſtollen worſhip, unwarranted novations, and uſurped exerciſes are ſo ſweet to ſome, that they confeſſe,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:23592:7"/>that when they are wearied with labours in the day, yet they ſpend a long time in the night at theſe meetings, without ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which they can not do at the ordinarie publict exerciſes of Gods worſhip in the day time. Naturally all men are inclined to obey humane traditions, more ſtrictly than Gods ordinances. One preaching at the privie meetings is ſweeter then many in a lawfull ordinarie way, and many come together for privie pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who abhor the ordinarie publict prayers: So papiſts keep the feſtivall dayes of Saints more ſolemnly then the Lords Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths. 4. Some make this habilitie of night-waking an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove the lawfulneſſe of privie meetings, and night-meetings: But it may as well prove the lawfulneſſe of theft and of whoordome, which are done in the night by men who watch for that end; And papiſts who watch in the Canonicall hours of the night, ſhall as ſoone prove that poprie is lawfull.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Qu. Should not familie worſhip alſo be reiected, becauſe men meet privily thereat?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anſw. Not, for 1. it is Commanded of God, Deut. 4.9, 10. &amp; Deut. 11.18, 19. Pſal. 74. from 1. to 8. the uſurping meetings have no ſuch warrand, and therefore can not look for ſuch a bleſſing. 2. Families profeſſe their meetings before all men; they hinder none to come and try their exerciſes; but none come to the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping meetings, untill they be tryed to be of their opinion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quest. Doth not Gods Word warrand all privie meetings, for religious exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſaying Be inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</p>
                  <p>Anſw. 1. That warrandeth not people of civile Callings to preach, nor that Timothie ſhould leave his own kirk at Epheſus and encroach on other mens charges: He muſt teach in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, that is, at ordinarie and extraordinarie occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, only where he is called. 2. The apoſtles might not teach in Bithynia and Aſia, Act. 16.6, 7. nor among the gentiles, untill they were called after the Lords reſurrection, Mat. 10.6. &amp; 28.9</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quest. Is it not more comely thus to meet for edification, then to meet ordinarly for exceſsive drinking, and idle conference, as ſome Preachers have done?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anſ. 1. Both are unlawfull and exceſſive: the one exceedeth the limits both of their Chriſtian calling, and of their particular lawfull calling over other mens charges; the other exceedeth the neceſſarie and lawfull uſe of Gods benefits. 2. Thus Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus ſurnamed Juſtus, who was not choſen with Mathias to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:23592:7"/>be an apoſtle, and the ſons of Scaeva might ſay, It is more come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be an apoſtle than to betray Chriſt as Judas did; his offence could not warrand them to doe that charge, neither can the offence of Preachers juſtifie ſuch uſurpation. Becauſe the ſons of Eli abuſed their callings, ſhould Uzza and king Uzzia there fore doe the office of the prieſts. 3. Women may not ſpeake publictly: but if men would preach, let their gifts firſt be tryed, and let themſelves receive impoſition of hands by the Miniſtrie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt. May not two or three meet for private prayers ordinarly?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anſ. One perſon alone, or one familie alone may pray privat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ordinarly, Gods word warrandeth both; and if any come into the familie occaſionally, he may pray and uſe familie exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe with them, the Chriſtian calling warrandeth it: But perſons of ſundrie families may not meet ordinarly for that end; It is uſurpation, becauſe the publict Preacher or Reader only ſhould convocat perſons of diverſe families for divine ſervice, or in their abſence they ſhould depute another; ſeeing the charge is theirs, nothing ſhould be done of that kinde without their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currance. When there is no publict Miniſters, by reaſon of apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie and perſecution, the people then without uſurpation may provide for themſelves: and likewiſe when people dwell far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from Churches. If a Paſtour want a Reader, he himſelf ſhould do the office, or cauſe one do it with adviſe of his people.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. Some forbide fathers of families to interpret any paſſages of GODS word to their domeſticks.</head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>SHould the fathers of families interpret any Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to their domeſticks? Shall not their ignorance breed error and hereſies, making a falſe gloſſe on Gods word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> They ſhould teach them, making a true gloſſe, &amp; to that effect they ſhould frequently hear preachings, read and confer with others, and enquire of their Paſtors the meaning of doubtſome Scriptures; but ſome idle pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors labour not to underſtand the Scripture, and would diſcharge this exerciſe, becauſe they can not reſolve ſuch
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:23592:8"/>doubts. 2. Their ſympathie with the papiſts bringeth the ſame arguments, for hiding the light of Gods truth: for the papiſts ſay, that laiks ſhould not read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, leaſt their ignorance Breed error and hereſies. 3. Hereſies were never bred, but by the ignorance of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict preachers. The opinions of private men were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much regarded that men would follow them, to ſtrengthen their hereſies. 4. Paul ſpeaketh of a Church in the houſe of Nymphas, Col. 4.15. and in the houſe of <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>priſcilla, Rom.</hi> 16.5. Could theſe be kirks without interpretation of the word. 5. Many by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent catechiſing and teaching their domeſticks, became learned publict teachers, <hi>Qui docet indoctos, &amp;c.</hi> 6. The neglect of ſuch holy exerciſes rather breedeth hereticall opinions both in private and publict perſons. 7. Iudge not before the time? publict Preachers are not cenſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and condemned, untill their herefies be known, ſo ſhould private men be uſed; and though ſome were guiltie, yet the exerciſe it ſelf is lawfull and profitable to ſuch as uſe it well. Should planting of vines, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict preaching be diſcharged, becauſe <hi>Noab</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> were drunk with wine, and <hi>Arrius</hi> turned an heretick? 8. Hirelings, like papiſts, would have people ignorant, leaſt too much knowledge make them take notiſe of the ignorance, errors, and lewdneſſe of their teachers, they are not like <hi>Paul,</hi> who wiſhed that <hi>Agrippa,</hi> and all that heard him, were like him in all things, except his bonds. <hi>Act.</hi> 26. and <hi>Moſes, Numb.</hi> 11. <hi>wiſhed that all the people were prophets.</hi> 9. By theſe exerciſes publict preachings are better underſtood, which faithfull Paſtours ſhould
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:23592:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>deſire. 10. He that careth not for his familie in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall things, is worſe then an in fidell: if hee neglect ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things he is no better.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Who calleth private men thus to teach their families?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> GOD in his word, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.9, 10. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 11 18, 19. they are commanded to teach them, ſitting in the houſe, walking in the way, lying down and riſing up. The <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. from 1. to 8. biddeth men teach their children in all ages the teſtimonies and works of GOD. Where are they written, if not in his word? How can they teach them, if they ſhow not their meaning? This command is not ceremoniall but morall. The fift command willeth both parents and children to do their dueties: Naturall parents ſhould alſo be ſpirituall parents, in bringing up their children in nurture, and in the fear of the LORD. How can children fear GOD, without the knowledge of his word, ſee <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4. 2. When <hi>Paul</hi> deſired aged women to teach younger women Chriſtian dueties, hee made not humane philoſophie the ground of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, but GODS word, ſaying, <hi>That Gods word bee not blaſphemed Tit.</hi> 2.5. Of the dueties of familie exerciſe ſee the preceeding chapter, in the anſwers to the fourth queſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. They forbid all ſet formes of prayer.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHat is a conceived form, and what is a ſet form of prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> All ſet formes are firſt conceived, being formed according to his conception that prayeth; then if any ordein them to be uſed again, how often ſo ever, 1, 2.3. dayly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo far are they ſet formes, becauſe they are ſet &amp; appointed for a more freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t uſe, 2. When <hi>Chriſt</hi> in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:23592:9"/>garden prayed thriſe, uſing the ſame words. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. at the firſt expreſſion it was a conceived prayer, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards a ſet form, which he ſet and ordeined to be ſaid againe at two diverſe times. 3. If people concur, uſing the words of him that conceiveth, it is a ſet forme to them, for they conceive it not, their concurrance is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond expreſſion of the prayer, it is firſt expreſſed by the conceiver.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Do none pray nor wrestle with God by the Spirit, but in a conceived forme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> GOD commanded the high prieſts to bleſſe the people in a ſet form, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.24. Is not GODS Spirit the indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of all GODS word? 2. When the Iſraelites in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe began any journey, at the taking up of the ark <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>Ariſe O Lord, and let thine enemies bec ſcattered:</hi> and when the ark reſted, hee ſaid, <hi>Return O LORD, to the thouſands of Iſrael, Numb.</hi> 10. Our LORD in the garden ſaid thriſe a ſet form: and albeit the Euangeliſts differ in repeating the words of his prayer, becauſe they only poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the matter thereof: yet <hi>Mark</hi> at his ſecond, and <hi>Matthew</hi> at his third prayer, affirm that he ſaid the ſame words; and on the Croſſe His complaint was words of the pſalme 22.1. <hi>My God, my God, why baſt thou forſaken me?</hi> and His laſt prayer on the Croſſe was words of the pſalme 31.5. <hi>Into thy hands I commit my Spirit.</hi> Hee had never a greater preſence of the Spirit, nor a greater wreſtling with GOD againſt the ſenſe of his wrath; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Satan, death, hell, and all the power of darkneſſe, which he overcame by the ſame Spirit, who never left him in his greateſt agonie. 4. <hi>Paul</hi> in the beginning of ten Epiſtles, ſaid, <hi>Grace be unto you and peace from God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:23592:9"/>and from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> they ſay he might well do it, writing to ſundrie people: Thus they yeeld that ſome way he might have the Spirit, uſing a ſet form; but he wrot two epiſtles to the <hi>Corinths,</hi> and two to the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians,</hi> uſing this ſalutation, and two to <hi>Timothie,</hi> uſing another ſalutation. 5. In pſal. 57.1. are the words, <hi>Be mercifull to me,</hi> twiſe repeated. In pſal. 68.1. the foreſaid words of <hi>Moſes</hi> are repeated. In pſal. 80. is a ſet forme thriſe repeated, <hi>viz Turn us again, O Lord, and cauſe thy face to ſhine, and we ſhallbe ſaved,</hi> this is inſert among conceived prayers. In pſal. 136. which was dayly ſung in the temple, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.41. is a ſet form of praiſe 26. times repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>viz for his mercie endureth for ever.</hi> They who reject ſet forms of prayer, uſe often this ſet form of praiſe in meeter, which is but a paraphraſe of the text, 20 the ſet forms of prayer are paraphraſes of the LORDS prayer. 6. Chriſt who beſt underſtood the Spirit of prayer, heard and accepted the devotion of the people, crying, <hi>Hoſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> or, <hi>Save now, I beſeech thee,</hi> taken out of the pſal. 118.25. which the <hi>Hebrews</hi> affirm was yearly, ſaid at the feaſt of tabernacles: and <hi>Mathew</hi> 21. ſhoweth, that they often repeated the words, both before they came to the temple and alſo within it. The phariſies in their hypocriſie were offended thereat, but Chriſt defended and commended it. 7. The laſt prayer in the Scripture is a ſet form pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the coming of Chriſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.17, 20. <hi>The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and the Bride ſay, Corns,</hi> that is, the Spirit ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>keth in the church, <hi>viz.</hi> the regenerat, teaching her to ſay, Come: And <hi>John</hi> biddeth them that hear this propheſie, ſay, Come, and <hi>John</hi> himſelf prayeth in the full ſentence, ſaying, <hi>Come Lord Jeſus.</hi> 8. Set formes oftimes ſeeme
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:23592:10"/>to have more of the work of the Spirit then conceived forms, for after their firſt conception, other godly men, moved by the ſame Spirit reviſe them; they reteine the materiall, and cancell the ſuperfluous, and they alter and ſupplee words needfull: Thogh Gods Spirit inable men to pray, yet He ſuffereth humane frailtie to bee ſeene in their prayers, to humble them, he giveth no perfection of graces in this life, conceived prayers are not ſo well tryed, though ſome boaſt much of them in contempt of ſet formes.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Are any ſo infirme, that they have need of ſet formes, more than of conceived formes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Negligent paſtours never try it, neither know they that many people never underſtand, nor can imitate concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved formes, becauſe themſelves, and others whom they take notiſe of can conceive, they think that all men can conceive. But theſe following among others have more need of ſet formes, then of conceived formes: 1. Some weak Chriſtians of a honeſt life, and of good age, could never remember all the Lords prayer, as their Paſtours affirme, who diligently taught them: If they cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member a few words often repeated, much leſſe varietie of words never twiſe repeated. 2. Others learned the Lords prayer, but cold do no further. 3 Some learned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſet formes, by frequent hearing of them, but could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conceive. 4. Some uſing ſet formes a long time, in end became able to conceive once in the day, and they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo uſed dayly a ſet form for the weaker ſort. 5. Some children could pray nothing at all, untill they had uſed ſet formes, but afterwards they conceived. 6. Some by a diſtempered brain can not conceive when the diſeaſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, but at other times they conceive; few congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:23592:10"/>want ſome of theſe, if they have not all. 7. It is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eloquent and powerfull prayer with God, if a humble heart groan under the burden of ſin, with faith and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent deſires of mercie and ſanctification, though they can ſcarſlie expreſſe three words, without theſe all varietie of words and conceptions is but babling. <hi>Moſes</hi> at the red ſea, and <hi>Anna</hi> at the houſe of the Lord in <hi>Shilo,</hi> prayed in the ſpirit of prayer, not uttering one word: He is a blinde judge that meaſures inward grace by outward eloquence. 8. If there were but one of thoſe weak ones in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, a faithfull Paſtor ſhould uſe ſet formes, to teach them to pray for their private uſe: they are cruell and mercileſſe ſheepheards who neglect the weak ones in a mater ſo needfull for ſalvation. 9. And when they are helped, with a better conſcience they may conceive for the ſtronger ſort.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>When I uſe ſet formes, men eſteeme baſely of my preaching, &amp; account me unlearned, if I expreſſe not varietie of meditations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But when you conceive in the prayers follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they will change their thoughts. 2. For your eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation ſhould you ſuffer the weak ones to periſh, not teaching them to be acquainted with God by prayer. 3. The diſciple is nor above his maſter; the Lord and his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles uſed ſet formes, not fearing contempt, you ſhould do the like.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>When the Lord taught his diſciples to pray, he ſaid not Vſe theſe words, but, Pray after this manner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Evangeliſts write both to be after the Lords meaning. for <hi>Math</hi> 6. ſaith, <hi>Pray in this manner: Luke</hi> 11. ſaith, <hi>When you pray, ſay, Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. The ſpeech of <hi>Matthew</hi> who did firſt write the Goſpel, can not be the interpretation of the ſpeech of <hi>Luke,</hi> who
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:23592:11"/>had not as yet written it; for the cuſtome of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhoweth, and the order of nature requireth, that the interpretation ſhould bee given after the obſcure words, but not before them. 2. If the LORDS prayer conteine things needfull for us, we may uſe the ſame words, to expreſſe the ſame things, which CHRIST the wiſdome of the Father uſed: If it ſignifie not things needfull, it were a fools ſacrifice to pray after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thereof, ſeeking things needleſſe. 3. Therefore mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Chriſtians more wiſely do conclude their own pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with it, acknowledging thereby it to be more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and ſignificative, than any prayer conceived by ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man. 4. Some call it hard and obſcure, Preachers ſhould explaine obſcure Scriptures, chiefly which are dayly in uſe. If thou think it obſcure, thou canſt not form a prayer like it, nor imitat the thing thou knoweſt not: nevertheleſſe uſe this prayer, for the Lord unto whom nothing is obſcure, knew that it meant things needfull for thee, and pray the Lord to hear thee after his own meaning in it. 5. Some ſtrain out a gnat, and ſwallow a cable, abhorring all ſet forms of prayer, and yet after Divine ſervice they ſay the bleſſing in a ſet forme.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>It is not mentioned in Scripture, that the apostles ſaid the Lords prayer, Ergo we ſhould not ſay it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Charitie ſhould perſwade us that they obeyed the Lords commandment in uſing it, ſeeing no Scripture ſaith the contrate: Many of the apoſtles had they never faith and repentance, nor the love of GOD, and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red they never their parents, becauſe particular mention of theſe things are not in Scripture.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Is it not a tautologie to conclude our prayers with the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:23592:11"/>Lords prayer, ſeeing we have prayed for the ſame thing alreadie</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A tautologie is a needleſſe repetition of the ſame words or mater, but when we repeat the ſame things, to ſhow the vehemencie of our deſires, it is not needleſſe. 2. A conceived prayer repeateth oftimes the ſame mater though it change the words. 3 To this effect, the Lord in <hi>Math.</hi> 6. after the Lords prayer, taught us to ſay the word <hi>Amen,</hi> which ſummarly includeth in it the whole prayer. 4. Every repetition includeth in it ſelf a new complaint, as if you would ſay, I am not ſufficiently ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted in the aſſurance that my former words were accepted, therefore I pray again for the ſame things No man hath power and authoritie from GOD, to abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate or deſpiſe any form which GODS word approveth.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>If we uſe ſet formes, we ſhould only uſe the Lords prayer, for no other forme is enjoined to us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The apoſtles alſo uſed other ſet forms, and ſo do we: they ſpake by the Spirit in uſing them alſo.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>In Numb. 6. the Lord ſaid, Thus ſhalt thou bleſſe, that is, in this manner: Hee ſaid not, Vſe the ſame words. Ergo the Priests uſed not a ſet form of bleſſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thus import the ſame ſenſe, then it is a ſet form of ſenſe: why may not the ſame ſenſe have the ſame words? ſeeing the words are a manner of ſpeaking, as the ſenſe is a manner of ſignification: no words can better expreſſe the ſame ſenſe, then the words that Gods Spirit hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. 3. The text ſhoweth that the prieſts ſhould have u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſame words: for the Lord ſaith, Thus ſhalt thou bleſſe, ſaying, <hi>The Lord bleſſe thee,</hi> they are bidden ſay, <hi>The Lord bleſſe thee,</hi> this is the manner how they ſhall bleſſe. 4. Albeit the prieſts had uſed only conceived words, yet the deſpiſers of ſet formes bleſſe only in a ſet forme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. What call you ſtinted prayers? Are they lawfull?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:23592:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Both prayers and divine praiſe are ſtinted, when men willingly reject the ful libertie of uſing them which GOD hath granted. GOD in his word hath given us alike warrand and libertie, to uſe both conceived and ſet forms of prayer, hee that rejecteth any of the two, ſtinteth to himſelf the form which he uſeth, and reſtraineth the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie which GODS Spirit hath granted in rejecting the other form. The papiſts in their ſervice book have ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſet formes: others ſtint unto themſelves conceived forms; though they alter the words, yet they ſtint the form: but we ſtint neither the form nor the words, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, 1. we uſe both the forms: 2. we ſometimes change the formes, a ſet form into a conceived form, or we uſe diverſitie of ſet forms in the ſame purpoſe, and ſo we ſtint not the words of a ſet form. 3. At the end of a concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved prayer wee ſometimes ſay a ſet form, as the LORDS prayer, or the bleſſing, &amp; ſometimes we conceive words at the end of a ſet form. 4. Sometimes we mixe words of a ſet forme among conceived words.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Do not many through envie complaine that we ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteine from ſet forms, becauſe themſelves want eloquence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ</hi> It is as true in ſome who want it, as it is true in others who have it, that they deſpiſe ſuch as want it. 2. But it is not true in many both private and publict per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who have as much eloquence as you have, and yet they uſe ſet forms, not onely to countenance the lawfull practiſe of Chriſt, his prophets and apoſtles, but alſo, becauſe GODS Spirit worketh by it, and warrandeth it in his word, as he doth conceived formes.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Should not all men conceive at all times, for Gods word proveth that all men can conceive, as</hi> Ioel 2.18. <hi>I will
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:23592:12"/>poure out my Spirit upon all fleſh, and</hi> Zacharie 12. <hi>I will poure out upon the houſe of David, and upon the inhabitants of Jeruſalem the Spirit of grace and ſupplication.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thus you prove that both private and publict perſons can conceive, which we deny not of ſome; but negligent paſtours know not that others can never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, nor yet underſtand mens conceptions, they know not paſtorall dueties, who know not this both of young and aged perſons. 2. But you make a falſe gleſſe on theſe texts, as if the pouring out of the Spirit in <hi>Joel,</hi> were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a giving of the gift of conceiving prayers. <hi>Peter Act.</hi> 2. interprets it to be the extraordinarie gifts of the Spirit, given unto GODS ſervants in a greater meaſure then was uſuall, as diverſities of tongues, propheſies, viſions, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of miracles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and alſo the ordinarie gifts, as faith hope, charitie, humilie, temperance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were given more largely: and you interpret the Spirit of grace and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in <hi>Zacharie,</hi> to be only the gift of conceiving pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as if Chriſt, his prophets and apoſtles wanted the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of grace and ſupplication, when they uſed ſet forms.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Are not conceived formes of greater dignitie, and therefore wee ſhould not uſe ſet formes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Doth GOD aboliſh the Moon and Stars, becauſe the Sun is of greater dignitie? Shall a man cut off his little finger, becauſe the other fingers are ſtronger? Shall the Sacraments bee neglected, becauſe the Word edifieth more? 2. The two forms of prayer are of equall dignitie in theſe reſpects, <hi>viz.</hi> they have one author, the holy SPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIT, who dyted them in his Word: they are both in one language; they both ſignifie alike excellent and ſpirituall things, &amp; both alike able to ſtir up our devotion, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:23592:13"/>the LORD would not have uſed ſet formes in his greateſt extremitie: it is out corruption that hindereth us to make ſuch uſe of them: Eloquence and varietie of words are much admired by Pagans, and naturall men, like <hi>Agrippa,</hi> who was almoſt perſwaded to be a Chriſtian, and yet was void of ſanctification. Our corruption doth ſtill dote too much upon the ſame, though we be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſo that we contemn the other form which Chriſt and his Saints made uſe of. 3. All the prerogative of a conceived form, is, that it expreſſeth mo meditations than a ſet form; but it neither maketh our prayer more acceptable unto GOD, neither can it expreſſe more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent things. The examples foreſaid of Chriſt and his Saints do ſhow that GOD accepteth the one as well as the other; and if he make a difference, it is his cuſtome oftimes to reſpect more of the things which the world eſteeme leaſt of: ſo CHRIST in his greateſt extremitie chooſed a ſet form, as was ſaid before, ſee the reſt in the next chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. They forbid all reading of prayers.</head>
               <p>Qu. <hi>SHould not ſet formes be ſaid from the memorie, or from the heart? that is they ſhould be ſaid perqueer, ſeeing reading of prayers is not commanded in Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Neither repeating from the memorie, nor conceiving of prayers, nor ſinging of pſalmes on a book, nor off the book, are commanded in Scriptures, ſhould they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not be uſed? The dueties of prayer and praiſe are commanded, and theſe circumſtances are lawfull &amp; uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and no wayes hurtfull to theſe exerciſes. 2. Whether you read them out of the inviſible book of your memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or from the viſible book of paper, the words are alike
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:23592:13"/>heard by the people, and the devotion of both reader and hearer is alike ſtirred up thereby, if the corruption of our unruly hearts and itching ears hinder not.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Is it not ridicolous, if a child ask from his father bread or a fiſh on paper ſo is it to read prayers unto God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is as comely thus to ſeek benefits from God, as to praiſe him on paper for the ſame benefits at the ſinging of pſalmes.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>The pſalmes are the text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, read prayers are not ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Our pſalmes in meeter are not the text of Scripture, otherwiſe preachers ſhould make ſermons on them, they are but paraphraſes of the text, having the ſame ſenſe. So are our read prayers paraphraſes of the LORDS prayer, or of ſome petitions in it, for all things needfull are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally included in the LORDS prayer, and particularly in other Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Read prayers expreſſe not all our wants, Ergo they ſhould be rejected.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is no mater, if they contein things perpetually need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the Preacher at the end of his read prayer, or after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in his conceived prayers may expreſſe mo wants. 2. Neither doe his conceived prayers expreſſe all his own wants, nor yet the wants of the people, he never knoweth them all. 3. The Lords prayer concluding our prayers, may ſupplee all the omiſſions of our imperfect prayers, though wee know not all our wants. 4. Thy ſpeech reproacheth the LORD, and his ſervants, who ſought oftimes a ſupplee only of ſome wants. The Lord ſaid, <hi>Father, forgive them, they know not what they does If it bee poſſible take this Cup from mee. Abraham</hi> prayed for Children, <hi>Jacob</hi> for food and rayment, and ſafetie from his enemies, the apoſtles for increaſe of faith, <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:23592:14"/>that the meſſenger of Satan might be taken from him. Many prayed that Chriſt wold cure their diſeaſes, Chriſt never cenſured ſuch prayers, but phariſaicall holineſſe cenſureth prayers that expreſſe not all their wants, which their own prayers could never do. 5. If by faith we ſeek but one thing with inward deſires, and outward expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, this prayer is perfect in reſpect of the eſſence, and nature of prayer; ſo is every petition of the Lords prayer or the meaning thereof: but the whole ſumme of the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions is perfect, in reſpect of the enumeration of things needfull: this enumeration needes not be ſaid at all times (as the foreſaid example ſhew) though we have need to ſeek them dayly, we may ſeek mo or leſſe of them, as we are ſenſible of theſe wants.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is it needfull to read prayers publictly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, for many learned men of good under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and conception have weak memories, &amp; throgh diſeaſes in the head men ſometimes forget words, which at other times they remember: it is beſt therefore not to truſt in the memorie.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>It is ſaid We know not what we ſhould pray, Ergo we ſhould not uſe ſet forms, for men know not what matter is in them? Anſ.</hi> If we ſhould not pray when we know the matter, neither ſhould we conceive if we know the matter. 2. Much leſſe when we know not the matter, for <hi>ignoti nulla cupido,</hi> wee can not deſire the thing wee know not our deſires are the beſt part of our prayers. 3. But the text ſpeaketh of the manner, ſaying, <hi>We know not what to pray as we ought,</hi> and <hi>the Spirit helpeth our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and interceedeth for us,</hi> that is, he aſſiſteth us to pray, not with varietie of words and conceptions, but with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:23592:14"/>
                  <hi>groanings that can not be expriſſed</hi> by any form of prayer: the Spirit groaneth not, but he kindleth ſtrong deſire in our hearts, the ſervencie whereof cauſeth groanings. 4. Groanings both ſhow our earneſt deſires, and prove that we know the matter before wee ſeek it. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. ſaith, <hi>I will pray with the Spirit, and with the underſtanding alſo</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Doth not the Spirit help us alſo, by putting new me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations and new deſires in our hearts, which were not in our mindes when we began to pray, Can this be done with ſet forms?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Spirit helpeth us alſo at ſet forms, making us expreſſe the words with a deeper ſenſe of our wants, and with more fervent deſires of the things we ſeek, that oftimes we have not at the beginning of our prayers: both our conceived prayers, and ſet forms are but lip-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, if GODS Spirit thus help us not. He interceedeth for us, becauſe theſe and ſuch other of his graces in us, do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us to pray, and GOD heareth us, becauſe he reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth theſe graces, and work of his Spirit in us.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the Spirit of prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not varietie of words, and eloquent conceptions that ſome may have, without the ſanctifying Spirit, but it is an earneſt crying unto GOD, with faith and fervent deſires and groanings, in any form of prayer. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Anna,</hi> the mother of <hi>Samuel</hi> prayed with this ſpirit, expreſſing no words at all.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is not that prayer best, that cometh from the ſenſe of our wants?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> So it is and therefore ſet forms ſhould contein things perpetually needfull, and the ſenſe of them ſhould bee perpetuall as are increaſe of faith, remiſſion of ſins, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, and ſuch things as are in the Lords prayer: if any words of the prayer concerne the preſent time on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:23592:15"/>as war, famine, peſtilence, they ſhould be altered or removed, as the evils are changed.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Should the Church uſe the ſame meanes of Gods worſhip, both in her infancie and perfect age?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ceremonies are abrogat, our prayers are morall, for by them we confeſſe the LORD to be GOD in the firſt Command, we adore him in the ſecond, and we honour his Name in the third, uſing both the forme of prayer. 2. If a ſet form ſhould be abrogat, becauſe the church uſed it in her infancie, much more a conceived forme which was firſt uſed, for in it <hi>Abraham</hi> prayed for children <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 15. and for the <hi>Sodomites, Geneſ.</hi> 18. <hi>Jacob</hi> uſed it, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 32. The firſt ſet forms in Scriptures were ſaid by <hi>Moſes,</hi> at the lifting and reſting of the ark, 3. It was the fulneſſe of time, and a full age, when CHRIST and the apoſtles uſed ſet forms. Now it is like a doting age, when ſet forms which were in requeſt with them, are become taſtleſſe and loathſome to many. 4. As the church in her outward eſtate had an infancie, and perfect age, ſo hath every member thereof in all ages. Every man coming in this world, is as ignorant of GODS word and worſhip, as were the Patriarks at their birth; and ſome are ſo weak that diſcreet Paſtours ſhould uſe them like infants all their lifetime. It is as good reaſon to urge people to ſpeak all languages, becauſe the apoſtles did ſo, as to urge the weak, ones that have no eloquence, to conceive prayers, becauſe the eloquent do ſo: it is a tempting of GOD to require of people above their power.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Reading is not a prayer, but a receiving into the heart information from the words read.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> You ſhould ſpeak ſo of the hearing of both the forms
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:23592:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>of prayer. 2. We muſt firſt know before we ſpeak, we receive information by ocular reading, or looking on the book, and then we ſpeak to inform others, that they may concur with their deſires, and with a ſtill voice, and alſo we ſpeak to glorifie GOD with our mouth, as we do with our heart, that hee may hear us, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times true prayer may come from the heart alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. No Apocrypha ſhould be brought into publict aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, but onely Gods word, and the lively voites of his owne graces, mens writings are Apocrypha.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Mens ſermons, the pſalmes in meeter, and conceived prayers are not Canonick more then read prayers. 2. If they be the lively voices of GODS graces, ſo are read pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for godly men gifted with GODS graces firſt concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them, and they ſtill ſignifie the ſame things, and men having ſaving grace, uſe them as the firſt conceivers did in earneſt prayer, aſſiſted by GODS Spirit, ſo that they make uſe of them, as if themſelves had conceived them.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Mens writings are not without errour, they carie not ſuch majeſtie as the pen of the holy Ghoſt, they are not ſo authentick, confirmed by ſignes and wonders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Neither are mens unwritten conceptions ſo authentick</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Doe not read prayers reſtraine the libertie of GODS Spirit, who inableth men to conceive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not, for nevertheleſſe of them men may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive as much as ever they did. 2. Did Chriſt, his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Apoſtles reſtrain this libertie, when they ſaid ſet forms. 3. Seing GODS Spirit in his word indited both the forms, they reſtrain his libertie who aboliſh any of the forms from GODS publict worſhip, ſeeing GODS word which alloweth theſe forms is made publict to the world</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:23592:16"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is it not a quenching of the Spirit, to read other mens words, when I ſhould poure forth mine owne heart?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If you have the ſame wants, the words of a read prayer are yours, as well as theſe who firſt conceived them: GOD doth not appropriat words and ſpeeches to particular men: Thou wouldſt have people to concur with thy conceived words, which are no more theirs then read words; if the one be a quenching of the SPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIT, ſo is the other, for both are the words of other men, and both are ſet formes to the people that concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them not. 2. It is not a quenching, but a cheriſhing of the Spirit, to uſe reverently the gifts which he made uſefull to others, it is a quenching to deſpiſe theſe gifts. 3. Some being in ſtranger churches were much moved with ſet formes, thinking them to be newly conceived becauſe they never heard them before; but at the next hearing of them, they become loathſome: So it is not the form, but the noveltie of the words which pleaſeth mens itching ears. GODS word it ſelf often tepeated is loathſome to our corrupt nature. Some judge GODS SPIRIT to be like themſelves, delighting only in novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of words, and therefore they make idols of new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, affirming that GODS SPIRIT ſpeaketh only when men uſe new conceptions. The papiſts baniſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way conceived forms, others diſcharge ſet forms: True grace ſhould make us ſtrive againſt both theſe extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in the battell between the fleſh and the SPIRIT, for GODS Spirit indited both the forms in his word. 4. A ſet form at the firſt hearing is eſteemed a work of the SPIRIT, but afterwards unconſtant people deſpiſe the ſame words, as a work of Satan.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:23592:16"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Miniſters are called to preach, and not to do the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Readers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Then neither ſhould they read the pſalmes when they ſing, nor text when they preach, as did the LORD out of <hi>Eſay</hi> 61 1: in <hi>Luke</hi> 4. 2. Prayer is not preaching, if they be only called to preach, they ſhould not pray in any form. 3. Thus ſome confeſſe againſt themſelves, that a ſet form may be uſed, for they ſay it belongeth to Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. 4. If Miniſters be called to preach, then they may do the office of Readers, and they ſhould do it when they want Readers, for all GODS word are canonick preachings of GODS truth, his mercies, judgements, power, and wiſdome, and of his properties, works and wonders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Miniſteriall preachings ſerve for a further explication clearing of the ſenſe, and application of the canonick preachings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. Is not the reading of a prayer a neglect of conception, and a ſhamefull proſtrating of our ſelves to be ruled by men, even to the ſhame of our heavenly Father, who giveth unto us better gifts?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> There is no ſuch neglect, ſeeing you may conceive before or after the reading. 2. If you concur with a conceived prayer, the ſhame is as great you are no leſſe ruled by men, whoſe conceptions are no more thine then the conceptions of read prayers. 3. It ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not but it honoureth GOD, if you reverently uſe the work of his SPIRIT in others, but when thou deſpiſeſt that which he approveth in his word, on thy part thou procureſt his ſhame.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>To read a prayer when men may conceive, it is to bring the weak and the lame, when they have a male in the flock. Malac.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Anſw.</hi> But if I conceive before or after the read
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:23592:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>prayer, I offer the male alſo. 2. If I read a prayer with faith, with fervent deſires, and humble expreſſions, it is a male without blemiſh before GOD, through Chriſt: the Lord, and his apoſtles, and prophets offered ſuch males, reading ſet forms from the inviſible book of their memorie: So wee may read from the viſible booke of paper, which is an artificiall memorie. A book is a rich treaſure of conceptions, an artificiall memorie a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full providence of God, to help ſuch as are weak both of underſtanding and memorie.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Should not Chriſtians ſtudie to perfection and grow in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The grouth of Chriſtians is not in multitude and varietie of words and conceptions, for <hi>Tullius</hi> and <hi>Demosthenes</hi> might then have been Chriſtians who could be eloquent in any ſubject, even in Chriſtian maters, if they had midled with them, albeit they had been but hypocrits. 2. Neither conſiſteth this grouth in forſaking the form of prayer, which Chriſt the fulneſſe of all perfection, uſed and approved in others: but it is a grouth in holineſſe of life, heavenly knowledge, faith hope, charitie, fervencie in prayer of any form, and in other ſpirituall graces, and in doing good works. Our Lord in his greateſt perfection, ended his life, ſaying a few words, firſt conceived by <hi>David</hi> in pſal. 31.5. <hi>Into thy hands I commit my Spirit:</hi> and <hi>Steven</hi> ſaid, <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>If any that can walk perfectly, come to his father creeping or deſiring to be born by others, will it not offend his father, and procure a refuſall, rather than the benefits which be ſeeketh? So he that can conceive cloquently, if be read a prayer, or ſay a ſet form, and ſo is born up by other mens ſpeaches, be offendeth God, and procureth a refuſall of his benefits.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:23592:17"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hee that concurreth with conceived prayers, is as much born up with other mens ſpeaches. 2. Thus the high Prieſts uſing the words of the bleſſing which <hi>Aaron</hi> firſt ſaid, and the Prophets and Apoſtles uſing ſuch ſet forms, as are mentioned in the preceeding chapter, are here reproached as born up by theſe ſpeaches, or that they offend GOD, uſing ſet forms when they may conceive: and CHRIST is blaſphemed as an offender of GOD, and ſo is a ſinner, in repeating his owne words againe in the garden, and the words of the pſalme 22.1. and pſal. 31.5. if he might conceive; or he is blaſphemed, if they ſay he uſed ſet forms, becauſe he could not conceive. 3. Men walk uprightly both unto GOD, and with GOD, by true faith, in whatſoever form they pray, though blind zeale knoweth no walking, but by varietie of conceptions and eloquence. 4. Whether we read words, or ſay them from the memorie, expreſſing the ſame wants, the words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him that prayeth, as much as to the firſt concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers: As the light of the Sun is no more proper to them that firſt uſed it, then to ſuch as uſed it afterwards, ſo is it with words and languages, which are the gifts of the holy GHOST, whether men acquire them immediatly, as the apoſtles did on the Pentecoſt, or by ſtudies and edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: as all others doe.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is it not ſufficient that ſet forms be committed to Readers, for publict reading?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> When prelats did commit baptiſme, and the LORDS Supper to the inferiour Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, and themſelves did miniſter confirmation, it made the people deſpiſe the LORDS ordinances, and magnifie humane confirmation: So when Preachers commit the reading of prayers only to Readers, the people deſpiſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:23592:18"/>them, becauſe the Preachers deſpiſe them.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>I acknowledge the ſet forms in Scripture, for Gods Spirit did indite them, but the ſet formes out of Scripture have not ſuch authoritie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Neither have the conceived forms out of Scripture ſuch authoritie. 2. But GOD to whom we ſpeak hath as great authoritie when wee read our own ſet formes, as when we read GODS word it ſelf, then our reverence to GOD ſhould be no leſſe. 3. Seeing GODS Spirit was ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall with both the formes in Scripture, what reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his operation from the one more than from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of Scripture.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>The books of Diſcipline ſhow, that our firſt Reformers pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed not that ſet forms ſhould continue for ever in the church of</hi> Scotland, <hi>but only untill that God ſend ſufficient able men, but who can blame giftleſſe old and failed men to plead for a ſtoffe, helping themſelves to walk?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This reproach redoundeth to our bleſſed Saviour, and to his ſervants foreſaid, as if they wanted ſpirituall gifts, when they uſed ſet formes. 2. Few, or no preachers, ſince the firſt reformation were ſo unable, but they alſo uſed conceived prayers. 3. Therefore it ſhould be inſert in the books of Diſcipline, that ſet forms muſt continue in the church, for theſe cauſes: 1. For people that can not conceive, that by frequent hearing of them they may remember ſome words for their private uſe, rather then to pray nothing at all. 2. For preachers diſeaſed in the head, whereby their conception is troubled. 3. For o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preachers, leaſt afterwards they be diſeaſed, that then the ſuddain change of the form ſeeme not ſtrange unto the people. 4. Both to countenance their infirme bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:23592:18"/>and to countenance the LORD, his prophets and apoſtles, who uſed ſet forms not through infirmitie, but becauſe the words were ſanctified, and directed by Gods Spirit, and were as acceptable to God, and as able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their deſires, as new conceived words. They who love Chriſt, ſhould countenance himſelf and his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and their religious exerciſes chiefly when they are in contempt, as ſet forms are at this time: this is a confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt, and of his word before men. 5. For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the inſolencie of ſuch as are puft up with elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, doting ſo upon it, as if Gods Spirit were not effectuall without it.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Should any pray for the ſpace of dayes, moneths and years, untill that Gods Spirit come and aſſiſt them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They who want faith can not pray, though they uſe the words of prayer: yet no man ſhould be hindered to pray: for none knoweth what is in man, but his own Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: the Lord ſuffered babes to come to him, though they underſtood not the word which worketh faith. 2. They who have faith may pray at all times, for Gods Spirit ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leaveth his owne work, though ſometimes hee bee more or leſſe effectuall in them.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Should not theſe novations be received, ſeeing their defenders are of a godly life and converſation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The danger is ſo much the greater, for as a godly life helpeth to edifie, when men preach Gods truth, ſo the blameleſſe life of the phariſies, and of hereticks, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure great reſpect unto their hereſies and errours, which a profain life could never do. 2. When <hi>Paul</hi> perſecuted the truth, he was <hi>blameleſſe, touching the righteouſneſſe of the law, Phil.</hi> 3.6. 3. If they be godly in life, and of a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:23592:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſound judgement, when they conſider theſe things more deeply, they will glorifie God in forſaking them. It proceedeth not from Gods Spirit to deſpiſe the form of worſhip which Hee approved and commanded in his word: ſuch were the Lords prayer, the bleſſing of the prieſts, and the praying for the coming of Chriſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.) 4. None are more godly then Chriſt and his apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who uſed both the forms.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>If people concur with any prayer before the ſentence be ended, take they not Gods name in vain, not knowing what they pray for?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> So they do, if they concur by aſſenting, or ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Amen,</hi> before they know the full ſentence: it is a mocking of God to ſeek the thing they know not. 2. If the preacher pray for one that was ſick, and the people are informed that he is dead, it is ſuperſtition, if they concur: So is it, if hee pray that people may ſhow their humilitie, by kneeling to ſacraments or idols, or that they thankfully remember Chriſts doings and ſufferings, by keeping ſuperſtitious dayes: but they may concur with ſet formes, before the ſentence bee ended, if they have them in their memorie, becauſe they know the matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. Some interrupt Gods worſhip continually, read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the lines of the pſalme, by intermiſſions, in the</hi> time of ſinging.</head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>HOW is it that many deſpiſe ſet formes of prayer, and yet they praiſe God is ſet formes of muter: When did Gods. Spirit chooſe the one, and refuſe the other: both are paraphraſes, and not texts of Scripture, to vvit of the Lords prayer, and of the pſalmes. Some uſe a double ſet form, to vvit, the miter, and the proclaiming of linese this vvas never practiſed nor commanded in Scripture, as vvere the ſingle ſet forms of prayer and praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Blind zeal proclameth the lines, that ſuch as can not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:23592:19"/>read may ſing: but they neglect to repeat a ſet form (which is more needfull) that they may learn to pray privatly, rather than to pray nothing at all. 2 The miſeries of this life, and happines of the life to come, do ſhow, that prayer is more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit now, and praiſing of God in the next life; we have dayly motives of praiſe, but much more of prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quest. What errours are committed, in repeating the lines at ſinging?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. There is a continuall abuſing of Gods name in it, for men oftimes ſing divine praiſe, not knowing what they ſpeak of God, as in pſal 8.1. <hi>O God, our Lord, how wonderfull?</hi> One that hath not the pſalm in their memory, knoweth not if the works, or mercies, or fearfull judgements of God, or the great power and cruelty of the enemies be called wonderfull, untill that the line be ſung out, and the next line read. In pſal. 84.1. <hi>O Lord, ſince ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance doth to thee, &amp;c.</hi> three lines are ſung out, and the fourth read, before they know the ſentence; and weak memories forget what they ſing, before the ſecond or third line be read: ſome can not repeat the firſt line after the reading. They abuſe Gods name alſo when the laſt line is read, albeit they underſtand it; for it is a none ſenſe to ſing only apart, viz. the laſt line, &amp; not the whole ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence with underſtanding: and many underſtand not the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, even at the hearing of the laſt line, becauſe they forget the former lines before the laſt be read: ſo God is rather mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than praiſed by this blind implicit faith; modeſt ſilence hath more true devotion. 2. They ſay that learned men themſelves underſtand not many words which they both read and ſing. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance is tolerable, when God revealeth not the mater, but not when men procure it by a raſh practiſe, nor yet when they will ſeem wiſe in the thing they underſtand not. Will not a king be offended, if his ſervants ſpeak to him as drunken men, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they ſay, but more juſtly may God be offended at ſuch contempt. 3. The proclaimer of lines of times forgetteth the words of his book, and he ſpeaketh other words for them. 4. Sometimes his book is wrong printed, and he bableth, as he findeth it. 5. Sometimes people diſtant from him hear not his voice, becauſe he heareth his own voice, he believeth that all the reſt hear it. 6. It is a great contempt of Gods worſhip, at every line to interrupt and mar it, giving place to a reader. Will any
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:23592:20"/>interrupt the ſhearing of corn, by tilling ſo much ground as is ſhorn, at the ſhearing of every ſheaf: this interruption is more uncomely. 7. Muſick orderly uſed ſtirreth up mens hearts, to praiſe God cheerfully: this interruption diminitheth cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and hindereth attention unto the matter.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>It is comely in the church that one part of the people ſhall ſing, and nes all the rest?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ. It is as comely as when ſome read the word with the Reader, and the text with the Preacher; and as when ſome uſe ejaculations at preaching, and not all the reſt. 2. It is more comely than that all the people ſhall ſo often interrupt Gods worſhip, giving place unto a Reader. 3. Gods Spirit thought it comely, that twelve men only ſhould ſing at once in the temple &amp; not all the reſt, Chron. 25. the reſt may praiſe God in a vocall manner, ſaying with <hi>Iob, Bleſſed be the name of the Lord, Or, For thine is the kingdome, power and glory:</hi> for Chriſt in the Lords prayer did conjoin praiſe with prayer. 4. The Lord in Math. 11.25. ſaid, <hi>I thank thee O heavenly Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth, &amp;c.</hi> this was as true praiſe, as when after his laſt ſupper he ſung a pſalme. 5. At the Lords birth the ſheepheards heard, the Angels praiſed God, without reading of lines, for concurrance of the ſheepheards: this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall praiſe may ſuffice all the world, if the muſicall praiſe be not rightly uſed. 6. If men have in their hearts the ſubſtantiall praiſe of the love, reverence, and of an high eſtimation of God, the matter is little though all their lifetime they want the ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of muſicall praiſe. 7. The ignorant may be taught a more comely muſicall praiſe, without abuſing of Gods Name.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quest How ſhall it bee done?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Teach them to get in their memories ſhort and materiall pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes (for they are capable of badrie ſongs) that once or twiſe every Sabboth they may ſing ſome of them with the people: they may alſo ſing them in their houſes; and they may ſing the concluſion, Glory to the Father, &amp;c. It were better in the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths, after publict ſervice to cauſe them learn to read, then interrupt Gods worſhip with reading.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Why do ſundrie godlie men cauſe proclame the lines?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The blind zeal of ſome thinketh it the beſt cuſtome. 2 Others do it only till they find a fitter occaſion to draw unruly people to a better cuſtome, as the apoſtles did permit ſome I gall rites, Act. 15. which in themſelves were become dead, untill the eſtate of the church were better ſatled.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:23592:20"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>May we not thus ſing to gain ſuch as cannot read, as Paul gained the weak ones?</hi> 1 Cor. 9.</p>
               <p>Anſw. Blind zeal neglecteth that which is more needfull, viz. by repeating prayers to gain ſuch as can not pray: when as men may be good Chriſtians without muſicall praiſe all their lifetime. 2. Paul might not be an idolater, a drunkard, nor a blaſphemer, to gain others from theſe vices: but he might uſe or not uſe the legall rites, which in his dayes ſhould end, and be buried honeſtly without ſudden violence: he gained people from ſuperſtition, you teach them to be ſuperſtitious, making them ſo eſteem of muſicall praiſe, as if God could not be praiſed, and themſelves could not be Chriſtians without it; you teach them to abuſe Gods name and to be hypocrites, in ſinging words that they underſtand not, ſo their words &amp; mind agree not together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. We thus keep them from idle thoughts, vvhen others are in a holy exerciſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ. You draw them rather both upon idle thoughts &amp; idle words, when they ſing that which they know not. 2. Good Chriſtians do confeſſe, that oftimes in their beſt exerciſes of prayer and divine praiſe, when they underſtand the mater, they are aſſaulted with evill thoughts; Satan ſo hateth Gods worſhip what then can be expected of ſuch as know not what they ſpeak 3 When twelve perſons only did ſing at once, 1 Chron. 29. the Lord knew that their muſicall praiſe did ſtir up holy &amp; reverend thoughts of God in the hearers, rather then if the hearers had ſung without underſtanding: So Eliſha propheſied, not being cheared up by his own muſick, but by a miniſtrel, 2 King 3. when David danced and leaped before the ark, rejoiſing that God was preſent with his people, his joy was ſtirred up by the muſick of others, as well as if it were his own muſick, 1 Chron. 15.28, 29.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. Do not theſe Words pertain to all Chriſtians, to vvit, that they ſhould speak to them ſelve in pſalmes and hymnes, and make melodie in their hearts to the Lord? Eph.</hi> 5.22.</p>
               <p>Anſ. None can rejoice to the Lord, not knowing a reaſon of their joy, as they do who ſing without underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding: if the ſound of ſingers ſtir up their mirth and cheerfulneſſe, they not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the mater, it is a melodie in their hearts, but not to the Lord, except ſome holy meditations of their own minde concur with the ſound. 2. If they rejoice in the aſſurance of Gods favour and mercie, it is a ſpirituall ſong and melodie in the heart to the Lord, though it want outward muſick.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But in Coloſſ.</hi> 3.16. <hi>he biddeth admoniſh one another in pſalmes and hymnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:23592:21"/>
               <p>Anſw. When men know not what they ſing, they neither ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh; nor are admoniſhed by ſuch melody. 2. Paul admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth Chriſtians not to be like Pagans, who at their feaſts and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſions were delighted with badry, filthy, and protain longs, but they ſhould uſe ſongs of heavenly conſolation, and of ſpirituall admonitions and inſtructions tending to edification. <hi>See the end of Chapter 6.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. Some never ſing the words, <hi>Glory to the Father, to the Son, and to the holy Ghoſt: As it was in the beginning, is now, and ever ſhall be, world without end.</hi> Some ſing them at every paſſage of the pſalmes.</head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>ARE theſe words or their meaning in the Scriptures?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In <hi>Math</hi> 28. the Diſciples are bidden baptiſe <hi>in the name of the three perſons of the Godhead.</hi> In 2 Cor. 13.14. Paul prayeth to them. In Eſay 6.3. the three perſons are pointed at in the words, <hi>Holy holy, holy, &amp;c.</hi> In Revel. 4.8. is the meaning of the whole ſentence, viz. <hi>Holy, holy, holy, Lord God almightie, which was, and is, and is to come. In Pſal.</hi> 45.7. <hi>God hath anointed thee with the oyl of gladneſſe, above thy fellows,</hi> That is, The Father hath declared the Son to be anoynted with the holy Ghoſt, fully dwelling in Him, by whom His manhead is repleniſhed with gifts above all meaſure: And thus John, (1 John 2.27) calleth the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>the anointing that teacheth.</hi> The pſalm. 136. biddeth, <hi>Give glorie to God,</hi> pointing at the unity of his eſſence, in the words <hi>Iehovah and Adonai,</hi> and in the relative, <hi>His;</hi> and at the plurality of perſons, in the words, <hi>Elohim, Haadenim;</hi> And at His Unchangablenes and Eternity, in the words, <hi>His mercie endureth for ever.</hi> His mercy indureth not without Himſelfe, for it floweth from Him. In Pſalm. 110.1. <hi>The Lord ſaid to my Lord,</hi> that is, The Father hath ſaid to the Son: And in verſ. 2. the Holy Ghoſt is called <hi>The rod of thy ſtrength Hee is a golden Scepter, holden out to comfort the godlie, but an Tron Rod to bruiſe the Wicked. Item the three perſons are mentioned in the ſecond pſalme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. Should theſe vvords be ſung, concluding every paſſage of the pſalmes, or ſhould they never be ſung at all?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ. It is a neceſſary duety of thankfulnes, to make expreſſe mention of our benefactors, ſo far as we know them; ſuch are the perſons of the Trinity. The papiſts ſuperſtitiouſly ſaid theſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:23592:21"/>words at the maſſe, and at the end of every pſalm read in proofe, albeit they had read ten pſalms in an hour, as if the pſalms had no religious uſe without theſe words; others reject them alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. The papiſt by the frequent uſe of the words make great ſhew of holines, that men may take leſſe notiſe of their errors and hereſies. They who neglect the words make a great ſhow of preciſenes, that their erroneous novations may ſeem to be nothing elſe but preciſeneſſe. 2. Therefore theſe words, or words of the like ſenſe ſhould be uſed, becauſe the duty of thankfulnes ſhould diſtinctly expreſſe our benefactors: and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they ſhould be omitted, to eſchew ſuperſtition, and the appearance thereof, and to ſhow that God may be praiſed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing only the Unity of Eſſence, as well as the diſtinction of Perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. May vve not glorifie God, ſometimes expreſsing onlie one or tvvo of the perſons?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We may do it both in prayer &amp; divine praiſe: for as the wife is inriched by the riches given to her Husband, ſo is the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band by the riches of his wife: Matrimoniall union maketh their riches not to be divided. The ſoul &amp; the body, and all the members thereof are honoured, if a crown be put on a mans Head, a ring on his finger, a chain on his neck, becauſe of the naturall union of the members of the body, and becauſe of the perſonall union, which is a more ſtrict naturall union of the ſoul &amp; body: ſo if thou honour any of the three peiſons, it redoundeth to them all, not only becauſe they all work together in every work that God doth to the creatures, and therefore all the three merit the ſame glory &amp; honour, but alſo becauſe of their eſſentiall union in one Godhead. 2. This is practiſed in <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.20. <hi>Vnto God our Father be glorie. Paul prayed to the Father, and to the Son,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.11. <hi>and to Chriſt only,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.18. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.22. <hi>Peter glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſieth Christ,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Chriſt ſaid, Pray, Our Father vvhich art in heaven, Luk.</hi> 11.3. If then the Honour expreſly given to one of the three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, redound unto all of them, it can not be prejudiciall to any of the three, if the Honour be expreſly given to all the three. 4. Albeit neither the whole ſentence, nor the parts thereof were ſo expreſly mentioned in Scriptures, as they are, yet either this, or the like ſentence, with good reaſon ſhould be ſung in divine praiſe, becauſe not only the whoole book of the pſalms, but all the Scriptures, all Gods works, &amp; mercies alſo tend to the ſetting foorth of the praiſe &amp; glory of all the 3. perſons. 5. Chriſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:23592:22"/>might have commanded the Apoſtles to baptiſe in the name of Father only, or of God ony; but He commanded to expreſſe all the three perſons, to ſhow, that as we increaſe in the knowledge of God, ſo we ſhould expreſſe more punctually that which we know of God. 6. As for the laſt verſe of the 28. pſalme, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a ſhort prayer for Gods people, it is very pertinent to ſing it, or the like ſentence, with the words of praiſe foreſaid, becauſe prayer and praiſe agree well together: ſo Chriſt conjoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them together in the Lords prayer, adding to the prayer the words, For thine is the kingdome, the power and glory, &amp;c. and alſo it is fit oftimes to uſe ſuch ſhort verſes of prayer and praiſe, as we conclude the ſinging of pſalmes, that ſuch as can not read, may get theſe lines in their memories, to ſing them with the people, if they can do no further: this may be done without abuſing of Gods name, and it is uſed by many in a laudable cuſtome: Many of the pſalmes do conjoin praiſe and prayer, we then may do the ſame, both at the ſinging of pſalmes, and in our prayers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. Some after Divine Service bleſſe the <hi>People in a legall manner.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>SHould not the Preacher after Divine Service, ſay. The Lord bleſſe you,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> He ſhould ſay, The LORD bleſſe us, and ſave us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not excluding himſelf in a legall manner, for theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, 1. To acknowledge thereby his owne miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and that he hath need of bleſſing, as much as any of the people, and ſo he caſteth away phariſaicall holineſſe. 2. To eſchew Judaiſme: the prieſts did pray and offer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for themſelves, and for the people, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus their own ſinfull condition and miſerie, but they ſpake the typicall bleſſing to the people, in the ſecond perſon only, not including themſelves, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6. becauſe in it they were not to acknowledge their own miſerie,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:23592:22"/>but to typifie and repreſent CHRIST, who bleſſeth really and ſubſtantially, and of whoſe fulneſſe every man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth bleſſing, but he of no man: and therefore when CHRIST came in the fleſh, the Prieſt of <hi>Aorons</hi> ſeed being about to bleſſe the people, was made ſpeechleſſe, to ſhow that the true high Prieſt who bleſſeth really, was now coming in the fleſh, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. Then he that imitateth <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> in bleſſing the people, ſo far he denyeth CHRISTS co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the fleſh. 3. To eſchew affectation of grandour for though ſome honeſt man ſay, <hi>The Lord bleſſe you,</hi> &amp;c. through ſimplicitie and cuſtome, yet others do it in am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and deſire of preheminence, thinking the words in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.7. do militar for them, <hi>viz. The leſſe is bleſſed of the greater,</hi> &amp;c. But the ſenſe is, that GOD almighty is greater abſolutely, and every manner of way than all his creatures, becauſe he bleſſeth them really: and the high Prieſt is greater than the people, whom he bleſſeth typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally; not every manner of way, but by repreſentation on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: thus he repreſented Chriſt, who bleſſeth really; but ambitious men preach their owne pride, when they ſhould preach Chriſts humilitie; they bleſſe in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond perſon, to ſhow their affected vain grandour, that they may be eſteemed greater then the people, whoſe ſervants they ſhould be for Ieſus ſake, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5.) 4. To eſchew conformitie with antichriſtians, for it is alſo a popiſh rite: the popes in the years of their Iubilee, in their progreſſe through <hi>Rome,</hi> they ſtretched forth their hands towards the people, ſaying. <hi>The Lord bleſſe you my people,</hi> &amp;c. Their clergie in the Letany of the ſervice book, are ſaid to bleſſe ſuch as receive orders, including themſelves, but when they demit the people from the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:23592:23"/>communion, they bleſſe excluding themſelves, to ſhow that they are greater then the people. When the prieſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his divine ſervice, a biſhop (if he preſent) ſaith the bleſſing, to ſhow his grandour above the prieſts and the people. A deacon if he ſay the ſervice, if then a prieſt be preſent, he bleſſeth for the ſame reſpect.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Are not miniſters called to bleſſe the people?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That particularly pertained to the prieſts, as well as the bearing of the ark, and the burning of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe and ſacrifices, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.8. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.13. Mim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are not called to the one more then to the other. 2. CHRIST ſent them to preach the Goſpel, and not to bleſſe neither typically nor ſubſtantially; the one is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate, He taketh the other in his own hand: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his firſt preaching, he altered the form of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: the Apoſtles uſed not their forme of bleſſing, but prayed in other wordes. 3. If a preacher take bleſſing only for preaching, he may bleſſe the people as he doth himſelf, he is alike called to both. 4. Hee may bleſſe new marryed perſons, ſaying. <hi>The Lord bleſſe you, &amp;c</hi> becauſe he prayeth for a particular bleſſing, <hi>viz.</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpering of their new begun eſtate of marriage. 5. If any ſalute his neighbour, preſent or abſent, he may ſay, <hi>The Lord bleſſe you, &amp;c.</hi> that it may be ſhown unto whom the honour is given; for ſaluation is a kinde of honour gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to our neighbour, ſuperiour, inferiour, or equall, for intertaining friendſhip, it is uſed both among pagans and Chriſtians, but ambitious courtaſie ſhould not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude Gods worſhip: though by way of praiſe people may bleſſe GOD, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.21. and by way of prayer beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars may bleſſe Princes, are they therefore greater?
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:23592:23"/>When <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> bleſſed <hi>Abraham,</hi> he was greater in a typicall grandour, repreſenting Chriſt, but when he bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God, he glorified God as a ſervant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.19. &amp; unto <hi>Abraham</hi> he ſought a bleſſing from God as a ſupplicant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. May I not ſay, Bleſſed are they that hear Gods vvord, and do the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An</hi> You may ſafely do it, for it is a preaching ſentence, proclaiming ſalvation to ſuch as obey GODS word. 2. It excludeth neither preacher nor people, and ſo it is no note of ſingularitie nor pride.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Some ſay, that the prieſts bleſsing vvas no prayer, but a ceremoniall bleſsing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether it be a prayer, or a bleſſing, if it be ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, it ſhould not be uſed. 2. Thus you may ſay, the moon is no planet, it is but a moon, the words are in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perative mood, therefore they import either praying, counſelling, or commanding. Is GOD inferiour to the prieſts, that they ſhould command him? Is he weak wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or raſh in his interpriſes, that they ſhould counſell him? 4. The Hebrews who beſt underſtand the words, take it for a prayer: ſo <hi>Maimony</hi> diſcourſeth of it in a treatiſe of prayer. 5. Some ſay that the words are equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent both to a propheſie, and to the pronouncing of a bleſſing, ſo were the words of <hi>Noah,</hi> ſaying, <hi>God perſwade Japhet to dwell in the tents of Sem:</hi> but that hindered none of their words to be prayers: the form of pronouncing of bleſſings, which are alſo propheſies, but no prayers, are written in <hi>Deuter.</hi> 28.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. Others reject presbyteriall government.</head>
               <p>Qu. <hi>IS it lawfull, ſeeing Gods church is independent upon any, except Chriſt, as their ſupreme, and abſolute ruler &amp; head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If that independencie forbid preſbyteriall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, much more ſhould it forbid civile govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:23592:24"/>which doth leſſe participat in ſpirituall things, and therefore is leſſe able to rule according to GODS word. CHRIST only hath ſupreme and abſolute authoritie, to rule in all lawfull government: In church government mens lives and conſciences are ruled by church diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and by GODS word, the ſword of the Spirit: In po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie civile laws, and the civile ſword muſt rule people, but their ſword and laws muſt alſo be ruled by GODS word. 2. All creatures depend immediatly upon. GOD in their bodily and ſpirituall exiſtence, and being in the ſecret providence whereby he overruleth their actions and operations, and in the ſecret bleſſings which he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to his bodily and ſpirituall benefits; but in giving the outward benefits themſelves, and in keeping people inorder, they have a mediat dependance on GOD, by u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his appointed outward means: thus <hi>Salomon, Prover.</hi> 8. ſaith, <hi>By me Kings reigne, and Princes decree juſtice.</hi> See <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. Of church government, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Math.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Whatſoever you ſhall binde or louſe on earth, ſhall be bound or louſed in Heaven.</hi> 3. The budding of <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> rod, and the giving of the keyes of the kingdome of heaven to the apoſtles, are infallible witneſſes, that GOD hath ordeined church government to be miniſtred by certaine perſons, qualified to that effect: and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very member of CHRISTS church hath not this power, ſee <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2) 4. If any offend his brother, why ſhould the offended perſon tell him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſecretly, next before one or two witneſſes, thirdly to the church, ſhould not the Lord only take order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, becauſe of independancie? ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15, 16. 5. <hi>Paul</hi> in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. ſpeaketh of three ſorts of elders,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:23592:24"/>
                  <hi>viz.</hi> paſtours who labour in the word, interpreting and applying it: Doctors who only interpret it, and ruling El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders who labour only in diſcipline: ſome make only two ſorts of elders, <hi>viz.</hi> ruling and preaching elders, for both paſtors and doctors preach Chriſt. Preſbyteriall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a ruling of GODS church by theſe elders: if it were unlawfull, <hi>Paul</hi> would not vouchſafe double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour on theſe that rule well. 6 Preſbyteries, ſynodall and generall aſſemblies are meetings of ſuch elders for preſbyteriall government, the paſtor with his elders ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his parochin in ſmall matters, remitting greater to the other aſſemblies. 7. Every man knoweth not all things, therefore matters to be agreed upon are more cleared when manyeſt wits meet together, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and authoritie is greater, when manyeſt votes agree together. Though <hi>Paul</hi> was an apoſtle, and <hi>Barnabas</hi> a diſciple, yet the church of <hi>Antiochía</hi> ſent them with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſciples to the apoſtles, and elders at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> (they being a greater number of qualified men) for the clearing of things queſtioned at that time, <hi>Act</hi> 15.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Seing a congregation is a perfect church, and hath all things perteining to a church, may they not chooſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a Paſtour, without conſent of a presbyterie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The foreſaid independancie doth not warrand it, more than that a preſbyterie ſhall appoint a paſtor unto a pariſh, without conſent of the people. 2. Every familie, and every member of Chriſt hath the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependencie, then every familie by it ſelfe alone, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſon by himſelfe alone, have as good warrand to chooſe to themſelves paſtours without the conſent of a congregation 3. If a congregation hath more power
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:23592:25"/>and authoritie than a particular perſon, this taketh away independencie, or immediat dependencie in outward go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: ſo the profeſſors of independencie do: ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh a dependencie in popular authoritie, whereupon particular perſons depend. 4. GODS word, the rule of mens lives, and of all outward government, dependeth not upon men in the being, and ſecret keeping thereof, for GODS Spirit dyted it, and his ſecret overruling power protecteth it, but the outward power of keeping it, and taking care to ſee it obeyed, pertaineth to civile rulers, who are <hi>Cuſtodes intriuſque tabulae,</hi> they ſhould ſee both church and common-wealth obey it: This is civile go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, the outward power of right dividing and applying of it, and of puniſhing the offenders miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, pertaineth to church rulers, this is church govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: this rule warrandeth not people alone to chooſe their paſtors, nor paſtors alone to chooſe their flocks. 5. No congregation, nor particular perſons have any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that pertaineth to a church, without CHRIST their head, the fulneſſe of all perfection, by whoſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit his ſervants were directed to appoint preachers, as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> the Gentiles chooſed not <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> but the church of <hi>Antiochia</hi> were commanded to ſend them to the Gentiles, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. And when they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained elders in every church, the people chooſed them not by themſelves alone, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. The <hi>Baereans</hi> choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> but the brethren ſent them to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea, Act.</hi> 17.10. and <hi>Paul</hi> committed GODS flock to the elders at <hi>Miletum,</hi> whom the holy Ghoſt had made their overſeers, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. The cities of <hi>Crete</hi> alone chooſed neither <hi>Titus,</hi> nor their preaching elders, but <hi>Paul</hi> left <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:23592:25"/>to ordeine them; <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. then contemne not the miniſteriall authoritie, for CHRIST, the fulneſſe of all perfection, hath given to them the miniſteriall keyes of the kingdome of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Doeth not both civile and church government perteine to every member of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, in reſpect of the good and profite effected by them, but not in reſpect of their adminiſtration: as the benefits of ſight, hearing, and ſpeaking, perteine to the whole body, and to every member thereof, but the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and actions of hearing, ſeeing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> perteine only to the eyes; ears, and mouth. So peace and proſperitie, the benefites of theſe governments, perteine to every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, but the adminiſtration of Iuſtice and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> perteine only to ſufficient qualified men, choſen to be rulers. 2. They urge impoſſibilities who would have all Chriſtians to be rulers, for infants can not ſpeak, young children want underſtanding. GODS word biddeth women be ſubject to their huſbands, albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it they have the ſame independencie with them: the moſt part of men are diſtracted in their callings by ſea and land: men abiding at home can not rule altogether: If all ſpeak. Command, and give out laws together, who can hear and obey? all ſhall be in confuſion: therefore GOD commandeth, nature inclineth, and neceſſitie forc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth theſe governments to be exerciſed by a few perſons fitted and choſen for that end. I have not deſcribed the offices and government of elders, but I prove their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to be lawfull, which ſome denyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:23592:26"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Some forbid the baptiſme of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren before their years of diſcretion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>QV <hi>SHould any be baptiſed, before they underſtand the articles of their faith, and give an account thereof in the Years of diſcretion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> All the apoſtles, except <hi>Paul,</hi> were baptized, before they knew many articles of the Belief, as the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Chriſt, repreſented by the water, his reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, aſcenſion, ſitting at the right hand of GOD, and his coming againe in judgement: neither underſtood they the things ſignified by the LORDS Supper, though they heard them from His mouth, untill afterwards. 2. They that were circumciſed, knew not the myſterie thereof, being but eight dayes old: therefore all people ſhould be partakers of GODS ordinances, ſo far as they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable as did the apoſtles, and the circumciſed. Infants are capable of outward baptiſme, but not of the Lords Supper, neither of the meaning of any Sacrament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>It is ſaid, that Miniſters admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by biſhops, are not lawfully called.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>ARE any lawfully called by biſhops or prelats?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If any admitted by the miniſtrie degener into<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ambitious preiats, the miniſteriall power not being right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken from them by church diſcipline, they may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully admit others to the miniſtrie, but nor to ambitious prelacie, nor to teach erroneous doctrine. 2. If bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops bee lawfully deprived of their miniſteriall office, their admiſſion of others is null. 3. If any ſtart up from a civile perſon to epiſcopacie, not being firſt a miniſter, his admiſſion of others, like as of other civile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, is of none effect: No man can give the power which hee never received. <hi>John Baptist</hi> did preach and baptize, not being called of men, but of GOD.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:23592:26"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Some forbide to converſe, or praiſe GOD in the ſocietie of infidels or ignorants.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SHould we ſing pſalmes, or exerciſe divine ſervice with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, ignorant, or reprobate people?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The LORD and his apoſtles never debarred <hi>Judas</hi> from their divine ſervice. 2. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide a while with <hi>Philip.</hi> The Prophets fled not from <hi>Saul,</hi> when he propheſied amongſt them. We ſhould ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate our ſelves from the wicked, and come out of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> in forſaking their idolatrie, and known ſins, leaſt we be guilty through practiſing or countenancing them: but if their ſins be hid, their ſocietie are not guilty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. 3. Knoweſt thou the ſecrets of the heart better then CHRIST and his apoſtles, who ſerved GOD, and preached dayly among infidels for their converſion. 4. If thou be ſincere, and void of phariſaicall pride, thou will rather condemn thy ſelf than others, as did the Publican, and <hi>Paul</hi> called himſelf <hi>the greateſt of all ſinners.</hi> 5. Some at the LORDS ſupper did abhor to take the elements from the hands of laicks, as they ſaid, leaſt they had beene wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, warlocks, or profain. For the ſame cauſes alſo they might refuſe to take them from miniſters for neither can they know their hearts, and the miniſters might abhor to take back againe the cup from the people, or to give them the elements. Notable apoſtats ſhould be eſchew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; apoſtaſie it ſelf excommunicateth them from true profeſſors, except they repent. 6. How ſhall infidels bee converted, if the faithfull converſe not with them, chiefly at Divine ſervice?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:23592:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Some forbid Preachers to read the books of learned men, for understanding Gods Word.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>SHould Preachers read the Commentars of godly fathers and learned men, for inabling them to preach Gods word: for the Lord in</hi> Matth. 10.19, <hi>ſaith, Take no thought how or what you ſhall ſpeak, for it is not you that ſpeak, but the Spirit of your heavenly Father that ſpeaketh in you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hee forbiddeth only exceſſive care and feare, when they are accuſed before judges, for the teſtimonie of the truth, but not when they preach, though at preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo they ſhould not exceed in fear. 2. The like ſpeach is in <hi>Matthew</hi> 6.25. Take no thought what you eat or drink, or put on: Did they therefore alwayes go faſting and naked, not uſing the means? 3. In <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.23. he telleth what they ſhould ſpeak. 4. He bad them hear corrupt teachers, <hi>viz.</hi> the Scribes and Phariſees, when they ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeat: that is, when they teach conform to his doctrine. 5. The Spirit brought to their memories the things that CHRIST taught them, and ſo helped them that uſed the means, <hi>John</hi> 14.26: 6. The Lord himſelf made uſe of the learning of the Doctors, hearing them, and asking them queſtions, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.46. Hee made uſe of their ſpeaches, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. <hi>viz. When it is evening, you ſay it will be fair weather,</hi> &amp;c. the like is in <hi>Luke</hi> 12.5. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.16. In his doctrine and parables he made uſe of the cuſtomes and doings of the people. 7. Some ſpeak of morall things with a mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accent, calling it a preaching from the heart, and from the Spirit, thogh they never interpret GODS word, which is the chief intention of the Spirit in preaching, and the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:23592:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>chief duety of the miniſteriall calling practiſed by the LORD and his apoſtles, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.21. and 24.27. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.4. and 8.3. and <hi>Act.</hi> 7.) GODS word it ſelf clearly opened is the moſt powerfull meane to enlighten the minde, to move the heart, and to waken the conſcience. 9. Why ſhould <hi>Timothie</hi> give himſelf to reading and meditation, and commit the things hee heard of <hi>Paul</hi> to ſuch as ſhould teach others, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13.19. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.9. And why deſired <hi>Paul</hi> the books and parchments left at <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. if they were taught only immediatly by the Spirit at preaching? 10. <hi>Paul</hi> maketh uſe of the ſpeach of <hi>Epimenides Cretenſis,</hi> a pagan. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12. <hi>viz. The Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians are alwayes lyars, evill beaſts, ſlow bellies:</hi> And of a ſpeech of <hi>Aratus,</hi> the <hi>Athenian</hi> poet, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28. <hi>Wee are alſo his of spring:</hi> that is, the ofspring or creatures of GOD: and of the inſcription which the Pagans wrot u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the altar at <hi>Athens, Act.</hi> 17. <hi>To the unknown God:</hi> and of the ſpeach of <hi>Menander,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.33. <hi>Evill ſpeaches corrupt good manners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>We interpret Scriptures by other Scriptures, and ſo we ſhow the meaning of the Spirit in his word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is good to ſuch as know the other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs already, but to others it is like words of an unknown language. 2. The illuſtration of obſcure Scriptures by other ſcripturs is no interpretation, except the words be plainer nor the obſcure ſcripturs: the words that are moſt in themſelves, cannot be interpret by other ſcripture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are no plainer words in ſcripturs. Item things that are but once written in ſcripturs, cannot be explained by other ſcripturs, as the ſpeach of <hi>Lomech, Geneſ.</hi> 4.23. <hi>I would ſlay am in in my wound, &amp;c.</hi> and the decree of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus,</hi> taxing all the world, <hi>&amp;c. Luke</hi> 2.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:23592:28"/>
               <p n="3">3. The LORD did interpret Scriptures by things which were not in Scriptures, as in <hi>Luke</hi> 4.21. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.5, 9, 14, and 27.43.46. verſes: <hi>Act.</hi> 8.33.) 4. To repeat the ſame things from diverſe Scriptures helpeth our faith in ſhowing the agreement of the writers, but it interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not, except the words repeated be plainer: therefore uſe alſo for the ignorant literall expoſitions and illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions uſed by learned men, and amplifie them for their capacitie.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Men ſhould not read, nor preach any thing but Scriptures, for</hi> Paul <hi>ſaid,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. <hi>I determined not to know any thing but Chriſt, and Him crucified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is, Hee would know nothing as principally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to his calling, but the doctrine of our ſalvation, procured by CHRIST and his ſufferings: all other ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and learning ſhould be ſervants unto this, otherwiſe how did <hi>Paul</hi> know the means of learning foreſaid. 2. Some affirm that themſelves ſpeak nothing but the texts of Scripture, which they never did, nor can doe, except they only do the office of readers: for neither the ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of their method, analyſis, and diviſion of the text, nor their doctrine, application, and uſes, nor the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of chapters, and verſes are in the text.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>In uſing the works of learned men, you ſeeme to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their errours, who alledge the church, or counſels, or fathers, or popes, to be ſupreme judges of contraverſies, and infallible interpreters of Gods word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Then CHRIST and his apoſtles ſhould alſo ſeeme to do the ſame, for we imitate their practiſe. 2. If a king or his deputies make people underſtand his laws, by the manner of ſpeaches and words of the people, are the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:23592:28"/>people therefore interpreters of the laws: So is it if we interpret GODS word, uſing the ſpeaches of men.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>How hath Christ interpret Gods word in the Scriptures?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By making ſome Scriptures ſo evident, that they need no other interpretation from the Scriptures, if the reader underſtand only the language: Such are theſe, Are they not twelve hours in the day? The ſervant is not greater than his maſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This evidencie and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is in ſtead of an interpretation. 2. By providing other plainer Scriptures, for opening up of obſcure ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. 3. Though wee finde not the meaning of ſome Scriptures, yet we finde ſufficient for our edification.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Some forbide the Scriptures to be read without interpretation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>IS it not lip-labour, and idle words, to read the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures publictly without interpretation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> All the Scriptures can not be read without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, for many Scriptures do interpret others.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But alſo they must be interpret by the studies and commentaries of learned men, otherwiſe he that readeth them is like a woman holding out a toome pape void of milk, that the infant can not feed thereon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw. Peter</hi> calleth GODS word ſincere milk 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3 therefore it feedeth by it ſelf: hence he and other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles wrote epiſtles without ſuch interpretation. Some milk is thin, that children may eaſily feed on it, ſome is hard and curded, which muſt be made thin and rarified by hearbs: So ſome of GODS word is plain, and eaſie to bee underſtood, ſome Scriptures are hard and obſcure, but they are rarified and made plain, that people may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:23592:29"/>their Preachers by prayer, meditation and read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, obteine of the LORD the underſtanding, the gifts of interpretation, right applying and dividing of the word of the old and new Teſtament, which are the ſpirituall papes of the church: theſe gifts are the hearbs which ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie this milk, and make it plain for the peoples capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. 3. The obſcure ſcriptures ſhould be read, for that which is obſcure to ſome is plain unto others; and alſo GODS Spirit can help our faith by obſcure ſcriptures, as when CHRIST cured the blinde with clay, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe maketh blinde. This is known, when men ſay in their hearts, I know whatſoever you obſcure ſcriptures ſignifie, it is for my well; and if it be needfull, GOD will revale it to me. 4. <hi>Moſes</hi> without interpretation did read publictly the books of the law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.7. <hi>Joſua</hi> did the ſame, <hi>Joſ</hi> 8.34, and <hi>Shaphan</hi> the ſcribe, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 22.10. The Eunuch read <hi>Eſay, Act.</hi> 8.28. <hi>Philip</hi> reproved him not for it: though he underſtood not the particular, yet hee might bee edified by ſome generals in it, before that <hi>Philip</hi> taught him: he ſaw in the words a rare exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of patience and humilitie, fit for his imitation, <hi>viz. One led like a ſheep to the ſlaughter, that opened not his mouth</hi> againſt his perſecutors. No chapters in the ſcriptures wanteth ſome plaine things in generals or particulars.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Propheſies and obſcure Scriptures ſhould bee read and heard as reverently and attentively as the diſciples heard obſcure things out of CHRISTS own mouth, and they learned humilitie, not being wiſer than CHRIST, making a gloſſe of their own upon his words, but pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently did attend, untill the LORD after his reſurrection, and the holy Ghoſt after his aſcenſion did teach them.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:23592:29"/>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>John</hi> calleth them bleſſed that heareth and readeth this propheſie, though many things in it be not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and therefore could not be interpret, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.3.7. The forbidding to read GODS word publictly, is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct forbidding it to be read altogether, which increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth antichriſtian darkneſſe: for if it be like a toome pape read publictly without interpretation, what milk can it give privatly: See the next chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIIII. <hi>Some deny the office of publict Readers to be lawfull.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>THe charge and office of publict readers, is it allowed by Gods word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is as warrantable as the charge of publict preachers, 1. for <hi>Moſes</hi> a prince and a prophet was commanded, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.11, 12. to read Gods word publictly, when the people ſhould appear before the LORD, that men, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, children and ſtrangers may hear and learn, and fear the Lord, and obſerve the words of the Law. 2. Gods word is written, that it may be read; therefore it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Scripture: Neither is publict nor private reading forbidden in ſcripture, both are commanded and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The Eunuch of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> read privatly, and <hi>Moſes</hi> publictly: ſo did <hi>Joſua</hi> and <hi>Shaphon.</hi> mentioned in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer chapter. 3. The Scriptures themſelves are cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick preachings of Gods properties, his works, mercies, judgements, providence, and promiſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therefore they ſhould be read publictly, either from the viſible or from the inviſible book of the memorie, if they can do it: but the reading on the viſible booke is more ſure. 4. <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 13.27 teſtifieth that the Prophets were read every Sabboth Day. This was done without interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:23592:30"/>for he ſaith, <hi>They knew not the voices of the Prophets,</hi> therefore they could not interpret the things they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not; but CHRIST and his apoſtles did interpret them. 5. Preachers are alſo readers, for they read their texts publictly, before they give the ſenſe, ſo did <hi>Nehemie</hi> chap. 8. and CHRIST <hi>Luke</hi> 4.) They who diſſallow the publict reading of GODS word, contradict themſelves in practiſe, for they are publict readers, when they rehearſe publictly the Lords prayer, or the bleſſing from the book of their memorie, and the text the ground of their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: yea, they and all the people read publictly the paraphraſes of the pſalmes, when they ſing them in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with a loud voice in the open aſſemblie: much more ſhould the canonick Scriptures themſelves be read pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lictly. 7. Neceſſitie alſo forceth publict reading, for poor people that can not read, may not ſuſte in readers to their private families, therefore they muſt hear publict read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or elſe they ſhall never hear at all: Alſo it is a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring of GOD to heare his word reverently before men. If the miniſteriall preachings be called Gods word much more the canonick preachings, dyted immediatly by GODS Spirit, are his word, but who can hear it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a reader?: then it appertaineth to the kingdome of darkneſſe, and of antichriſt to diſallow this charge. 8. It is objected that ſome readers are drunkards or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faine, but that ſhould not hinder reading more then preaching, for ſome preachers have the ſame blemiſhes. 9. It is objected that they underſtand not many things which they read: ſo many make ſermons on texts which they underſtand not, but none hindereth the lawfull try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of the life &amp; gifts of ſuch as enter in both the callings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:23592:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Private prayer of Preachers in the pulpit, and of people in the Church, is forbidden.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>IN a publict aſſemblie ſhould a Miniſter pray privat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the pulpit before he begin his publict exerciſe? Is it not idolatrie or ſuperstition, as ſome affirme, or oſtentation, or againſt decencie and good order, ſeeing he hath prayed for the ſame things alreadie in his chamber?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. Chriſt that night that He was betrayed, prayed thriſe in the garden for the ſame things. 2. If within the church a Iump of a wall fall down upon the preacher, ſhould he neither pray to God nor man for relief, becauſe he prayed for Divine protection in his chamber. 3. If men aſcribe divine vertue or merit to the prayer, becauſe it is ſaid within the pulpit, it is ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie: if they think it a more religious worſhip done in the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit then elſe-where, it is ſuperſtition. If they do it to be ſeen of men, rather then to glorifie God, it is oſtentation: if the matter of the prayer be not holy, and the manner be not in reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and humilitie, ſeeing the place is ordeined for a holy uſe, it is undecent, and againſt good order: But who can know the ſecrets of mens hearts? Therefore all publict religious exerciſes may with as good reaſon be diſcharged, for theſe evils may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie them alſo.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Can private prayer edifie in a publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct aſſemblie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Practiſe and example edifieth as well as preaching. 2. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample maketh people ſeek a bleſſing for their hearing, as the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor doth for his preaching.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>In a publict aſſemblie, ſhould not preachers and people concur in doing the ſame publict actions?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> They ſhould concur in the ſame mater, but not alwayes in the ſame manner and actions: at publict prayer all ſhould pray, the Preacher with a loud voice, the people in their hearts with a ſtill voice. At preaching all ſhould be exerciſed in the word, one in preaching, the reſt in hearing it: but at divine praiſe all ſhould ſing with a loud voice. In a publict houſe men may pray for particular bleſſings to themſelves, with as good reaſon, as in a private houſe they may pray for the church militant. 2. A publict houſe may admit private exerciſes, as duely as a publict perſon may have private affaires: So Chriſt in the temple bad
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:23592:31"/>one whom He healed, Sin no more, John 5.14. So ſaid He to the woman taken in adulterie, John 8.11. So in a church men may meditat, read privatly, and do the private actions of faith and repentance: So the Preacher firſt conſidereth every word in his minde, leaſt he preach in publict unadviſedly, and out of purpoſe. 3. At any time of the preaching men may ſend up eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, without concurrance of the reſt, and why may not the preacher do ſo before his publict exerciſes, whether the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple be ſinging pſalmes, or hearing the word read? But when he entreth in publict, their exerciſes ſhould give place to his more publict exerciſes; for they may read and ſing at home when they can not have preaching. 4. At reading the word only, at ſinging of pſalmes a paraphraſe of the word only; but at preaching, both the word, and paraphraſes, with the interpretation, doctrin and application are ſaid: therefore other exerciſes ſhould give place unto it, as unto a greater ſhining of the ſpirituall light of the ſame word.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Did not the Lord forbid his Diſciples, in Matth.</hi> 6.5. <hi>to ſtand in the Synagogues, and corners of the ſtreets, at private prayers: Ergo privat prayers ſhould not be in a publict place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It was never forbidden in the Scriptures. 2. Becauſe hee forbiddeth to doe after the meaning of all theſe words to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, forbiddeth he therefore to do after the meaning of any part of theſe words ſeparat from the reſt? He forbiddeth not to pray, nor to pray ſtanding in the ſynagogues, and corners of the ſtreets, nor to pray deſiring to be ſeen of men; but that they ſhould not pray ſtanding in the ſynagogues, and corners of the ſtreets, deſiring to be ſeen of men, as the hypocrites do, for they do all things for oſtentation and humaine praiſe, as the Lord faith of the Scribes and Phariſees, Mat. 23.15. ſo they abuſed faſting and praying, and giving of almes. 3. For eſchewing of hypocriſie, and vain glory, he bad the diſciples do theſe things ſecretly, as well as openly, which hypocrites do not. 4. They ſhould do theſe things before men, not for humaine praiſe, but to provock others to do the like, and to ſhow, that they are not aſhamed to glorifie God before men: they ſhould alſo do them privatly, to be exerciſed in the ſinceritie of well doing, and to be frequented with the neglect of humane praiſe, and thereby to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:23592:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>acknowledge that they are in the preſence of the Al ſeeing God, before whom they dare not be idle from well doing: they ſhould eſteem it a greater honour, if God alone behold them doing good, then if all men and angels were looking upon them. 5. The affecting to be ſeen of men at private prayer, is oftimes a notable glorifying of God: So <hi>Daniel</hi> prayed 3th the day, opning his windows of ſet purpoſe to be ſeen of men. Anna the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Samuel prayed privately in the Temple, in the ſight of men, 1 Sam. Chriſt prayed for himſelf before men, Ioh. 17.1. and he willingly heard many praying to himſelf before men, as Jairus for his daughter, the thief on the croſſe, the Cananitiſh woman, Mat. 15. Peter prayed the Lord to waſh his hands, head and feet, John 13. the Lord corrected the matter, but not the manner of his prayer. 6. The Lord in Mat. 5.16. ſaith, <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your heavenly Father.</hi> No good works have mo heavenly vertues ſeene in them then prayer; faith is ſeen in it, for we believe that God heareth us, and hope for we expect a good anſwer; and charitie, for in the Lords prayer we pray for others, as we do for our ſelves; and holineſſe, praying not to be led into tentation; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, in deſiring only dayly bread; patience, in ſuffring; and meekneſſe, in pardoning wrongs, in the words, As we forgive them that ſin againſt us: the zeal of Gods glory in the firſt three petitions a thankfull praiſing of God, in this confeſſion, For thine is the kingdome, the power, and the glory, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. May any pray privatlie in a publict place, where there is no aſſemblie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. They may, becauſe of the reaſons foreſaid, whether they be forced thereto, becauſe they want ſecret chambers, or becauſe the church is the moſt ſecret houſe they can finde; or, becauſe occaſionally they are in it, when they would pray, or men are hindered by other buſineſſe; to goe to their chambers, being far diſtant from them; or becauſe men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point churches for private as they doe for publict prayers, the one is as comely as the other; but men make decencie a reaſon for every thing, for the which they can not finde a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:23592:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI. The principall opinion of the Antinomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>or Libertines.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>The first propoſition conteining their chief tenet.</head>
                  <p>EVery faithfull Chriſtian being united to CHRIST by faith, is one with Chriſt, &amp; Chriſt with him therfore as it is impoſſible for Chriſt to ſin, ſo for the Chriſtian.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the union of two diverſe natures make the united parts alwayes equall in properties, then the body is immortall, inviſible, and an underſtanding ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, like the ſoul, for they are united in one perſon; and all the members may hear and ſee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe they are one body with the ears and eyes; and every faithfull man is almightie, infinit, and eternall God and man in one perſon, for they are united to Chriſt, God and man. 2. If any be united to Chriſt, the Iuſt are united to him: but <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, they fall ſeven times a day, <hi>Prover.</hi> 24.16) 3. Before that <hi>David</hi> was made King, GOD teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of him, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.21. I have found a man according to myne owne heart: This was not the decree whereby GOD ordeined him to be holy, it was a divine teſtimonie: yet after this, though he had union with Chriſt, hee fell in murther and adulterie, and hee numbered the people. 4. <hi>Job</hi> 3.1, 2. curſed the day of his death, through impatiencie. <hi>Lot,</hi> whoſe righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſoule the <hi>Sodomites</hi> vexed, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. fell in inceſt, and drunkenneſſe, See propoſition 3. and 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>The ſecond propoſition.</head>
                  <p>THough Chriſtians ſo long as they are but children in grace ſhould have their hearts filled with ſuch fear of God, as Scripture recommends, yet when they attaine unto perfect
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:23592:32"/>love, they ſhould bee void of all fear, Luke chap. 1. verſe 74.</p>
                  <p>Anſ. That text ſpeaketh of the fear of enemies, from which Gods people being delivered by Chriſt, ſhall ſerve God in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, not fearing them any more: this deliverance is now begun, and ſhall be perfited in the life to come. 2. Salomon, Proverb. 28.14. ſaith, Bleſſed is he that feareth alwayes; they can not be bleſſed without this perfect love. Moſes in Deut. 6.13. ſayeth, Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God, and ſerve him. Paul. ſaith, Philip. 2.12. Work out thy ſalvation with fear and trembling: He ſaith not, Begin the work like little children, but work it out like men of perfect age.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <head>The third propoſition.</head>
                  <p>CHriſtians effectually called, ſeing they want nothing of the glorified Saints, but the ſeparation of the ſoul from the body, they need not all pray for themſelves, but only for others. Therefore the Antimonians never ſay the Lords prayer.</p>
                  <p>Anſw. The propoſition is falſe, and the condition alſo, viz. that Chriſtians have ſuch perfection of glory in this life, Gods word proveth it not. 2. Salomon, 1 King. 8.46. 2 Chron. 6.36 ſaith, There is no man that ſinneth not; and Prover. 20.9. Who can ſay, I have made my heart cleane? I am pure from my ſin. David Pſal. 40.18. ſaith, I delight to doe thy will, &amp;c. This is a perfection in number, but not in degrees; for he ſubjoineth in verſ. 12. that his iniquities are mo than the hairs of his head; and in verſ. 13. he prayeth for himſelf. They who are not effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually called, can neither pray for themſelves, nor for others. David alſo in pſal. 51. and 6. and 143. and elſe-where. Daniel greatly beloved of the Lord, Dan. 9.18, 19. Steven full of the holy Ghoſt, Act. 7.55.59. Elias 1 King. 18. The apoſtles after they had received the holy Ghoſt, Act. 4.24, &amp;c. Paul after he was raviſhed to the third heaven, 2 Cor. 12. Old Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon, Luke 2.29, &amp;c. all theſe prayed for themſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="proposition">
                  <head>The fourth propoſition.</head>
                  <p>CHriſtians effectually called have their ſouls refreſhed at all times with the ſenſe of Gods love, mentioned Rom. 4. The joy flowing from it actually, continueth without interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that it neither can nor ſhould be mixed with ſorrow,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:23592:33"/>upon any occaſion; for ſeeing they enjoy the preſence of God, the ground of their joy, the children of the marriage chamber ſhould not mourn.</p>
                  <p>Anſw. All creatures have continually the eſſentiall preſence of God The Regenerat have alwayes his gratious ſanctifying preſence; for Chriſt ſaid, I am with you unto the end of the world, Math. 28.20. But no Chriſtians in this life enjoy his intuitive pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, wherein is fulneſſe of permanent joy, without interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Paul raviſhed to the third heaven, had his joy iuterrupted by the meſſenger of Satan buffeting him: and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8, 9. ſaith, <hi>We are perplexed, but not in deſpair, caſt downe, but not deſtroyed</hi> Perplexitie interrupteth joy. 3. In 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. <hi>While We are at home in the bodie, we are abſent from the LORD</hi> his ſoul being in his body; he was ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of this abſence: 2 Job 3.1, 3. Curſed the day of his birth; and chap. 17.7. he ſaith, My eye is dim becauſe of ſorrow.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="proposition">
                  <head>The fifth propoſition.</head>
                  <p>A Chriſtian may get ſuch perfection of grace in this life, which after his effectuall calling needeth no more addition, according to that <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.15. <hi>As many as are perfect, be thus minded.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That place proveth the contrarie: for if their perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction needed no addition, why addeth <hi>Paul, That they may bee thus minded?</hi> The preceeding verſes, 12, 13, 14. ſhow, how <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſed himſelf not to have perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of degrees, but of numbers, for <hi>He forgetteth things bebinde, and reacheth unto things before, preſſing towards the mark,</hi> hee ſubjoineth, <hi>Let theſe who are perfect bee thus minded,</hi> that is, Let them ſtudie continually to have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in grace, preſſing towards the mark. 2. In <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.14, 15. he acknowledgeth that they who ſhould after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards be no more children, yet they ſhould grow in all things in CHRIST their head, and in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.14. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of himſelf, and of others, he ſaith, <hi>Though the outward man periſh, the inward man is renewed dayly.</hi> 3. <hi>Peter</hi> (2
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:23592:33"/>
                     <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17.18.) acknowledgeth that the people have a ſteedfaſtneſſe in grace, and exhorts that they fall not from it, but to grow in it. <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaking of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, chap. 17.9. hee ſaith. <hi>Hee ſhall be stronger and ſtronger,</hi> the Hebrew is, <hi>He ſhall adde strength.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="proposition">
                  <head>The ſixth propoſition.</head>
                  <p>TRue and unfeined repentance, though it be a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar grace of GOD, yet it ſhould have no place in the ſoul of a Chriſtian effectually called by grace, for three reaſons. 1. Becauſe the gratious pardon of GOD is not in part, but in whole, of ſins bygone, preſent, and to come, and therefore ſeeing pardon was obteined once, upon condition of repentance, the practiſe of repentance is not to be renewed: 2. Becauſe he that is born of GOD ſinneth not, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9. partly ſeeing the ſeed of GOD remaineth in him, and partly by reaſon of his union with Chriſt: 3. Where repentance is, there muſt be grief and ſorrow, but the joy of a Chriſtian muſt not be interrupted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. They ſay, The effectually called ſhould not repent: We ſay, They who are not effectually called can not repent, becauſe they want faith, the tree that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth foorth ſuch fruit: How then ſhall faith and true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance be found in the world? 2. If any be effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called, the Iuſt muſt be ſo called, but they <hi>fall ſeven times a day, and</hi> as often <hi>they riſe again:</hi> there is no riſing again but by repentance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer to the firſt reaſon.</hi> Pardon of ſin was alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined upon condition of faith, as well as repentance: If repentance muſt not be continued nor iterat, no more muſt faith; and ſo Chriſtians having once believed and repented, thereafter they muſt be infidels and impenitent
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:23592:34"/>Perſons, contrarie to the Scripture, ſaying <hi>The Just ſhall live by faith, Hebr.</hi> 10.28.) 2. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. ſayeth, <hi>The inward man is renewed dayly,</hi> ſee <hi>Luke</hi> 17.4.) 3. They ſay, Pardon is granted alſo for ſins to come but in the firſt propoſition they deny that the effectually called ſin any more, becauſe of their union with Chriſt, and in the ſecond reaſon of this propoſition they ſay the ſame: So Satan fighteth againſt himſelfe, his kingdome can not ſtand. 4. They ſay, Our bygone repentance is alſo for ſins to come: How can we repent the ſins we know not: we may depart from this life, to day, or at this hour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer to the ſecond reaſon.</hi> If any be born of GOD, it is the juſt men, but they <hi>fall ſeven times in a day.</hi> In 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8. it is ſaid, <hi>If we ſay we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves, John</hi> numbreth himſelf among them, he being a father of perfect age in grace, he calleth GODS people, <hi>My little children,</hi> 1 <hi>John.</hi> 2.1. Things that make ſin compleet and perfect, are finall impenitencie, and a full reſolution to ſinne, and a full deſire and delectation in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning without reluctation: they that are born of GOD ſin not in this kinde, their ſins come not to a full grouth, for before they ſin they ſtudie to eſchew it; in the act it ſelf of ſinning they ſtrive and wreſtle againſt it: when it is committed, they cut the threat of ſin by ſpeedie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; the ſeed of GOD by repentance choaketh this wicked grouth. 2. Our union with Chriſt taketh not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all inherent ſin in this life, but it worketh in us a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of all ſin, a ſorrow for ſins committed, a thirſt for righteouſneſſe, and it freeth us from the imputation, guilt, and puniſhment of ſin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere to the third reaſon,</hi> That the joy of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:23592:34"/>is interrupted. See the anſweres to the fourth propoſition.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="proposition">
                  <head>The ſeventh propoſition.</head>
                  <p>CHriſtians effectually called, are oblidged to ſing the pſalms of praiſe, as a part of their task in heaven, yet it is unlawfull for them to ſing the penitentiall pſalms, for ſo men make themſelves lyars, not being under the ſenſe of Gods wrath.</p>
                  <p>Anſw. No Scripture ſhoweth that any did ſing theſe pſalms when they were under the fearfull fenſe of Gods wrath, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a fearfull judgement, but at theſe times they prayed for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and relief all ſinging importeth mirth, though ſometimes ſorrow be mixed with it: The ſentence of James was evermore true, that in trouble men ſhould pray, and in mirth ſing pſalmes. Jam. 5.13.) 2. When Gods heavy hand was on David, his roaring and crying was fitteſt, Pſal. 32.3, 4. When he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his ſins, and had gotten aſſurance of remiſſion, he might cheerfully ſing the ſame words which he uſed in his prayer in his agonie: He made not the 51. pſalme in the time of his mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and adulterie, his forewardneſſe and reſolution to ſin would not ſuffer him, nor yet when his conſcience was fore troubled for ſin, the extremitie of his grief and ſorrow would not ſuffer him, but afterwards he made this pſalm, that in the midſt of his mirth he might glorifie God, by confeſſion of his ſins, and by calling to remembrance the fearfull eſtate that ſin brought him into. 3. As Chriſt after his reſurrection, and begin glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, receined ſome remembrance of his ſufferings and humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to wit, the marks of his wounds: ſo in our mirth we ſhould remember our ſin and miſerie, uſing the ſame words of the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiall pſalms, which we might alſo have uſed in our prayers. 4. Thus the moſt ſanctified men are not lyars in ſinging the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiall pſalms, becauſe partly they were under ſuch dangers; which now they remember in their mirth, or they are now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the like dangers, which if they have any confort, they may confeſſe in their mirth, or they deſerve the like evils, becauſe of ſin, which dayly provocketh Gods wrath; but his ſparing of them is equivalent to a deliverance from ſuch dangers, for albeit God loveth his children, he loveth not their ſin, but correcteth them for it, becauſe he loveth them, <hi>Prover.</hi> 3.12</p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:23592:35"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Qu. May we ſing pſalmes in time of great trouble, or ſenſe of Gods wrath?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anſ. We may, if in the mean time we have any comfort or aſſurance of our deliverance; but if all things ſeeme bitter or fearfull, we ſhould rather pray: So Chriſt that night he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed, after ſupper, he knew what troubles were at hand, but he was conforted in the affurance of a joyfull deliverance, and therefore he ſung a pſalme: but in the gardein, when his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort was abatted, and his agonie great, he only prayed: Thus Paul and Silas did ſing praiſes to God in the priſon, Act. 16. thus the holy martyrs praiſed God in the mids of the fire, and of other torments, looking that God will turn all to the beſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="proposition">
                  <head>The eighth propoſition.</head>
                  <p>CHriſtians effectually called, whether they pray or praiſe in the immediat worſhip of God, they ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly fixe their mindes upon GOD, and upon the divine purpoſes betwixt GOD and them, that though they praiſe or pray, ſo long as the body is able without wearying, the minde wandereth not for a minut.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That is to ſay, the minde can not be long upon a good purpoſe, for they meaſure the conſtancy of the minde with the ſtrength of the body, ſaying, <hi>So long as the body is able, &amp;c.</hi> The Lord ſhoweth that the body is not able to continue long upon a good purpoſe, without wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying, ſpeaking to his diſciples, that could not continue with him in watching and praying, <hi>viz. The Spirit is ready, but the fleſh is weak, Mat.</hi> 26.41.) 2. <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. ſaith, <hi>That in his fleſh dwelleth no good thing,</hi> and of his minde, he ſaith, <hi>To will is preſent with me, but how to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that which is good, I finde not:</hi> And in <hi>verſ.</hi> 23. <hi>I ſee a law in my members, warring against the law of my minde.</hi> Thus the fleſh in Chriſtians diſquieteth the Spirit, chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at divine ſervice, which the fleſh abhorreth, and the body hateth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:23592:35"/>
                  <head>The conformitie of theſe Novations with peprie.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Papiſts uſe alwayes privie meetings, and night meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in places where true religion is profeſſed; ſo do the defenders of theſe novations: 2. The hindering of the interpretation of GODS word in private families, as well as in publict aſſemblies, ſtrengthneth antichriſtian ignorance and darkneſſe. 3. They diminiſh GODS word who leave out the words of the text, as the papiſts left out the ſecond command; and they diminiſh it, who make the text but a cipher, and of no effect, as if it were left out: ſo doe the papiſts unto all texts that warrand conceived prayers, when they ſtint the ſet forms of the ſervice book only unto the people, ſo do others unto all texts that warrand ſet forms, when they ſtint conceived forms only unto the people; they uſe varietie of words, but they ſtint their prayers unto conceived forms, both doe reſtraine the libertie of GODS Spirit, who allowed both the forms. All men may make uſe of ſet forms, if their itching ears hinder not; but many weak Chriſtians are debarred from acceſſe unto their heavenly Father by prayer, becauſe they underſtand not, and can not make uſe of conceived forms and ſet forms are taken from them, except that ſome ſay the LORDS prayer, but no further: GODS word alloweth further, in that CHRIST and his apoſtles uſed alſo ſet forms. 4. They who hinder the reading of prayers on paper, reſtraine the liberty of ſet formes as they do, who hinder the reading from the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible book of the memory. 5. The ſinging of the pſalms at the reading of every line, is like praying in an unknown language, as the papiſts do, for both take Gods name in vaine ſpeaking without underſtanding. 6. The continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:23592:36"/>all uſe of the words: <hi>Glory to the Father,</hi> &amp;c. is a popiſh ſuperſtition, the conſtant neglect thereof is an antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianlike extremity, to hide by ſilence the chiefeſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pals of GODS truth. which ſhould bee confeſſed before men. 7. Papiſts alſo bleſſe the people in a legall maner. 8. Popiſh prelats are enemies to preſbyteriall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, taking upon themſelves the whole power of church government: ſo ſome pretended reformers would have the miniſtration of church government to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all the people, that none ſhould rule above themſelves. 9. The baptizing of children onely in the the years of diſcretion, is like popiſh confirmation, which is a baptizing of children in the years of diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as if the baptiſme ordained by Chriſt were of no effect. 10. Some deny that Miniſters admitted by biſhops are lawfully called, though ſome biſhops be actuall Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: popiſh prelats do take the power of admiſſion from Miniſters, if they be not biſhops: ſo both are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Miniſteriall authority. 11. <hi>Phariſaicall</hi> profeſſors ſeparat themſelves at divine ſervice, not onely from pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans but alſo from ſuch weak Chriſtians, as are not much reſpected among men: ſo papiſts are much addicted to ſeparation, men of Church office are ſeparat from the people, in that they are called clergy and the people la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iks: And prelats, as if they were more holy, are ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from the inferior orders, and they ſeparat all ſound pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors from themſelves by excommunication. 12. The forbidding to read the works of learned men and ſound writers, is oftentimes practiſed by papiſts, to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of antichriſtian darknes. 13. To forbid reading of Scriptures without interpretation, is a hindering of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:23592:36"/>people, as the papiſts do to read any Scriptures at all, for if people be perſwaded that publict reading edfieth not, what confort can they expect of privat reading? 14. To forbid the publict office of readers, bringeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo privat reading in contempt, and ſo it maketh for hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods truth. 15 To forbid privat prayer in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick place before people, it hindereth the glorifying of God before men, in a worſhip wherein God ſhould be moſt glorifyed; ſo Antichriſtianlike it obſcureth Gods glory. To forbid privat prayer in churches, whether people be preſent or not, it maketh a ſuperſtitious diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of places, as if God ſhould not be worſhipped in every place by Chriſtians in their generall calling, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts made the like difference between the body of the church, and the chancell or quier. 16. The Antinomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are members of Antichriſt, for they are enemies to faith and repentance the chief doctrine of the Goſpell they either contradict or pervert the Scripturs in all their tenets. 17. All the humaine traditions, heriſies and errours, were brought into the church under the pretence of pietie and reformation of religion, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny embraced them through blinde zeal: thus are the foreſaid novations brought in, none of them have war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand from Scripture, which is GODS revealed will.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>An addition to the foutrh Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 26. <hi>the Lord ſaith to the Apoſtles, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>oſt cometh, he ſhall teach you all things, and bring all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> go we ſhould only uſe conceived prayers, for the Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> conceptions, and bringeth them to our memories?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. When Chriſt, his prophets, and apoſtles uſed of times
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:23592:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>words which were ſaid before, had Gods Spirit no medling with theſe words, becauſe they were not new conceptions. 2. That text ſpeaketh chiefly of preaching, which was the proper end of their particular calling. If they ſhould not preach, uſing meditation, reading, and other mens travels, as means to help them, but only look for new conceptions from Gods Spirit, it would almoſt ſeeme that prayer ſhould be ſo uſed, but the text proveth nothing of theſe. 3. The words of the text ſeeme ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to favour ſet forms of prayer; for the Lord ſaith, <hi>The Spirit ſhall teach, and bring all things to your memorie, whatſoever I have ſaid unto you:</hi> there is no mention here of new conceptions, but of things which Chriſt ſpake to them before; the text ſhoweth that Gods Spirit bringeth to mens memories things ſpoken before. 4. Gods Spirit giveth new conceptions, and maketh to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber old conceptions forgotten, and alſo to keep in memorie conceptions not forgotten; and he giveth men grace in their hearts to make uſe of all conceptions new and old, forgotten, and not forgotten, whether they be read from the viſible book of paper, or from the inviſible book of the memorie. 5. Then as the Sun and Stars are not only Gods work, when they are newly created, but alſo they ſtill remain Gods work; ſo the conceptions of devout prayer are not only the work of Gods Spirit, when they are newly dyted unto men, but they remaine ſtill his work, whether they be written or keep in memorie &amp; as it is a gift of God, that men may make uſe of the Sun and Stars newly created, or at any time afterwards; ſo it is the gift of Gods Spirit to uſe religiouſly any devout conceptions, when they are newly conceived, or at any time after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. The poeſie of Homer is his as well now as at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; ſo are the meditations of prayer the effects of a ſanctifying Spirit, as well no was before.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:23592:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The ſecond anſwers againſt <hi>ſome Novations.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Adde theſe to the Chap. 1. <hi>viz.</hi> Queſtion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SHould we not uſe privie meetings, for exerciſing our ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents; leſt they be given unto us in vain?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw. Davids</hi> brethren were ſtronger then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. The ſouldiers which <hi>Gedeon</hi> removed were ſtronger then the three hundred which he retained, but God glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifieth himſelf in doing great things by the imployment of the weak ones, and by the humble patience and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy attendance of the ſtrong ones: GOD did accept the zealous readineſſe of <hi>David</hi> in preparing materialls for the temple; as well as the travels of <hi>Salomon</hi> in building it. The ſervice done to GOD in the heart and intenſion, ſhall be as ſurely rewarded as the labours of the hand, if theſe things be done in faith: All the waters of a river and the clouds of the air attend on mens ſervice, though all be not imployed; So gifts given unto men ſhould glorifie GOD, either attending on his ſervice, or imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his ſervice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Adde theſe to the <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>SEeing the ſet formes of prayers in ſcripture are but ſhort tailed prayers, as ſome affirme, can they be fit for our imitation who uſe longer prayers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If ſhort prayers ſhould not be imitated nor uſed, then we ſhould neither uſe the Lords prayer, nor yet pray af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that manner as the LORD commanded. 2. Neither
<pb facs="tcp:23592:38"/>ſhould wee uſe nor imitat conceived prayers, whereof the moſt part in Scriptures are ſhort tailed, as they call them. 3 The longeſt prayer in Scripture was ſaid by <hi>Salomon</hi> at the dedication of the temple: It is twiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, <hi>viz.</hi> in 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6. Thus Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit indyted twiſe the longeſt prayer. Repetitions are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten indited by Gods Spirit, as in the 7 epiſtles. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.2. and 3. <hi>chap.</hi> In the beginning of every epiſtle is written <hi>I know thy works,</hi> And in the ending, <hi>Let him that hath an ear hear what the Spirit faith unto the churches.</hi> In <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. Chriſt ſaid 7 times: <hi>Woe be unto you Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees Hypocrits.</hi> In the books of the Chronicles are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hiſtories, which were in the preceeding ſcriptures: The 4 Evangeliſts oftimes repeat the ſame hiſtories.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is it not a ſufficient and ſubſtantiall prayer if the weak ones ſay, God help me, or be mercifull to me for Chriſts ſake, which they may learn at a conceived prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Much more is it ſufficient for the ſtrong ones, who have no need of ſo many helps; &amp; ſo they need not hear conceived formes, but they may learn at ſet formes to ſay; GOD help me, or be mercifull to me. 2. If then you conceive that the ſtronger ſort may have more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of mater &amp; words, uſe alſo ſet formes, that the weak may have more matter and words, which they can not have by conceived formes, which they can not imitat nor underſtand: They may groan or mourn at them only becauſe others do ſo, or becauſe it is a cuſtome.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>It is not mentioned in ſcriptures that the Apostles ſaid the Lords prayer. Ergo we ſhould not ſay it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Neither is it mentioned that they prayed in that manner: Should we therefore not pray in that manner?
<pb facs="tcp:23592:38"/>2. Neither is any prayer in ſcripture ſo compleat and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in parts as the Lords prayer. 3. Charity ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us that they obeyed the Lord uſing this prayer, ſeeing no ſcripture ſaith the contrary. 4. Many Apoſtles knew they not the ten commandements? had they not faith and repentance? and dyed they not in the Lord? al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they are not particularly mentioned in ſcriptures.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>It is more evident that they prayed in that manner, then that they ſaid theſe words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They never uſed in ſcriptures ſo compleat a manner: But if the matter was included in the Lords prayer, they uſed alſo ſome of the words of the Lords prayer. <hi>Christ ſaid, Father forgive them they know not what they do. Luk.</hi> 23 <hi>Not my will but thy will be done. Luk.</hi> 22. <hi>Father glorifie thy Name, I pray that thou keep them from evill. Joh.</hi> 17. Here are many words of the Lords prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Adde theſe to the <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>SHould not ſet formes be ſaid from the memorie or from the heart, or ſaid perquier, ſeeing reading of prayers is not commanded in ſcriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Neither is conceiving of prayers commanded in ſcriptures. 2. When <hi>Paul</hi> biddeth read his epiſtle. 1 <hi>Col.</hi> 4 16. He biddeth read all the prayers as well as other things in it. Such is the ſet formes in <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. Which ten times ſaid in his epiſtles. The valediction <hi>Chap. verſ.</hi> 18. See the like in 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5 18. When <hi>Iohn. Revel</hi> 1. <hi>verſ</hi> 3. calleth them bleſſed who read his propheſic, and Chriſt requireth if ſome had read the ſcriptures. <hi>Math.</hi> 12. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Luk</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. they did not except prayers. 2. In Rom. 15.4. Paul ſaith, <hi>Whatſoever things are written, are for our learning:</hi> how ſhall we learn them, if they be not read? And if we learn them rightly, we ſhould uſe them as the matter requireth: that is, we ſhould pray, if the words of prayer ſignifie things needfull for us; Be they words of praiſe, wee ſhould glorifie God; be they
<pb facs="tcp:23592:39"/>words of promiſe, ſtir up our hope; be they words of his law, learn obedience. If the words pray for ſuch as read the epiſtle, both the Readers &amp; Hearers thereof ſhould concur, as they do with the prayers of a Preacher, &amp; ſo theſe prayers are ſet forms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quest. How is Gods Spirit ſaid to interceed for us at prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. In that his graces planted in our hearts inable us to pray; and God heareth us, becauſe he reſpecteth theſe works of his Spirrt in us: Chriſt interceedeth for us, by meriting theſe graces; and the Spirit interceedeth, by working, and making them uſefull in us; and God heareth us, for the merit of Chriſt and for the work of his Spirit in us.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is the reading of prayers on a book lawfull, more then the reading of homilies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. No Scripture proveth the publict and private read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of homilies to be unlawfull, more then the expreſſion of preaching without reading; for Chriſt is preached both the wayes to our hearing, and Faith that cometh by hearing excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth none of the wayes: all the Scriptures are canonick preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of divine veritie, and are continually read: So holy mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall preachings, which illuſtrat the Scriptures, may as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be expreſſed with reading, as without it, chiefly when newly conceived miniſteriall preachings can not bee had. 2. Reading of homilies is ſometimes forbidden, not as unlawfull in it ſelf, but becauſe it maketh idle miniſters neglect their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and hindereth them to interpret many Scripturs, when they dwell upon a few homilies, for they are called to interpret all the Scriptures, ſo far as they can. 3. The frequent repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame homilies is not ſo needfull, as of the ſame prayers, for many weak ones can not at all learn to pray, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they hear the ſame words often repeated. Prayer is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in ſome meaſure of all Chriſtians; but though every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould admoniſh one another, yet it is not requiſite that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Chriſtian ſhould make preachings, which is the particular calling of the miniſtrie, but prayer belongeth to the generall calling of all Chriſtians. 4. If men forget any words of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, they may ſpeak other words of the ſame ſenſe for them, without prejudice to the weak hearer, who need not the words in their memorie, if they know the ſenſe; but if they forget words of ſet forms of prayer, though miniſters ſpeake other
<pb facs="tcp:23592:39"/>words of the ſame ſenſe for them, yet it perturbeth the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the weak ones, who can not learn to pray, except they hear the ſame words often repeated, and not diverſitie of words of the ſame ſenſe. 5. Then it is better to read ſet forms, for oftentimes the beſt memories forget words unawars: But they who eſteeme it Chriſtian perfection, to change evermore their conceptions, they want that excellencie of perfection, which Chriſt and his deareſt Saints had, in the ſubmiſſion of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the practiſe approven by Gods word, in praying heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ily, uſing the words which are read, and uſed by the Saints of former ages, when in their conſciences they know that theſe words expreſſe their wants.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. If a read prayer be lawfull, then you may cary your prayers in your pocket, or buy them in a book-binders ſhop, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ. If conceived prayers be lawfull, men may have them for a leſſe price, for they may conceive at their pleaſure, if the eſſence of prayer conſiſted in words heard or ſeene: But the words heard or ſeen are only images and expreſſions of prayer, as painted men and beaſts are but the images of men &amp; beaſts, though they be ſo named; ſo the naked images, and vocall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of prayer are called prayers: but if faith and fervent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires concur with the outward images and expreſſions, that prayer is a true prayer; and the inward deſires alone are more ſubſtantiall, and true prayers, then the outward expreſſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, though both ſeverally be called prayers. 2. Theſe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in a lively way teach us how to form our prayers; but the holy Ghoſt inableth us effectually to pray, whether we uſe the means of hearing, or ſeeing theſe images; ſo the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall prayers can not bee born in a pocket, or gotten from men, though the expreſſions may be gotten from men: it is only the expreſſions which men receive from miniſters, as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur, but the holy Ghoſt addeth true prayer to the expreſſions heard or ſeene.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. Chriſt after his aſcenſion gave gifts unto men to bee faithfully uſed, ſhould we then by reading neglect our conceptions?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ. You need not neglect them, ſeeing you may conceive as much as ever you did before, or after reading. 2. True grace is more known in uſing the baſeſt means, as Chriſt and his ſervants uſed, then to uſe the moſt glorious means that our loftie nature affecteth moſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. The Scripture biddeth us pray, it biddeth not read the words.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:23592:40"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Neither biddeth it conceive the words. 2. We are bidden drink wine in a cup at the Lords ſupper, we are not bidden drink in a cup of mettall or timber, ſhall we therefore uſe only cups of gold, rejecting ſilver cups? ſaying, they are not Gods ordinance, becauſe they are not expreſly commanded to be uſed at the Sacrament; and ſhall we ſay that cups of gold are Gods ordinance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we eſteeme moſt of them, when as God warrand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the one more than the other? So we are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to pray, without naming any form, yet we ſhould rather uſe both the forms then both theſe cups, for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of both the forms, but not of the mater of ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall cups, is mentioned in Scripture: Then when generals are commanded in Scripture we ſhould obey in ſuch particulars, as wherein true obedience may bee ſeene: So we may pray truely in any form read, or not read, if we do otherwiſe, the cauſe is not in the form, but in our corrupt naturs, that can not uſe the formes which the deareſt Saints uſed.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is it not idolatrie in Gods worſhip, to direct our faces towards a book? we ſhould look up to heaven, where God ſitteth in glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If thou canſt read turning thy back to the book, thy ſpeach would ſeeme to have ſome reaſon: But thou canſt not read without looking on the words, the book is not a religious object of adoration, but an object of neceſſitie. 2. The words are images of the things ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, if it be idolatrie to direct thy face towards them at prayer, ſo ſhould it be at the ſinging of Pſalmes, and at the reading of ſcriptures; for it is Divine Service to read GODS word for edification. 3. <hi>Elias</hi> upon mount <hi>Carmel,</hi> and our Saviour in the garden, without idolatrie prayed, with their faces towards the earth:</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:23592:40"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How many wayes doth Gods word warrand us to exerciſe ſpirituall dueties in particular circumſtances?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Three wayes. 1. When Gods word expreſlie commandeth the duety with the circumſtances, as when the Lord forbad his diſciples to faſt like the hypocrits, he bade them waſh their faces, and anoint their heads. 2. When ſcriptures bring exampls of the godly practiſing theſe duties in their circumſtances, as when <hi>Steven</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed kneeling. <hi>Act:</hi> 7. 3. It warrandeth by way of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, that is, it commandeth the general duety not ſhow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the particular circumſtances. But none can obey ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in circumſtances, which inable them to obey. Then Gods word which commandeth the duety expreſly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently commandeth to uſe the ſame circumſtances, becauſe without them they can not do the duety. Wee have a threefold warrand of ſetformes of prayer in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: 1. It is commanded as in <hi>Math.</hi> 6. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11. He ſets down the manner and forme of prayer. 2. We have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of ſet formes in ſcripture, as the bleſſing of the Prieſts, it was alſo commanded. <hi>Numb.</hi> 6. And Chriſt prayed thriſe in the ſame words in the garden. So did the Pſalmeſt in the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.3. By of conſequent the ſcripture proveth that ſuch as can not underſtand nor imitat new conceptions, muſt uſe often repeated concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or elſe they can not pray at all: And learned men though they can conceive, by the ſame conſequent they muſt uſe ſet formes, or elſe they can not teach the weak ones to pray: neither can they be free of the contempt of the practiſe of Chriſt, and of his ſervants, and of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie of GODS word, except they uſe alſo ſet formes. They ſhould not ſeeme wiſer but eſteeme it great wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:23592:41"/>to imitat them in things lawfull, which are neither cerimoniall rites that are abrogat nor miracles that can not be imitat. Then as Chriſt commanded to give almes to the poor, conſequently he commanded <hi>Peter</hi> to cure a creple, becauſe he had no other riches. He commanded to baptiſe with water, conſequently biddeth that in cold regions infants ſhould be ſprinkled, leaſt dipping in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter kill or hurt them. So in commanding us to pray, he willeth us to uſe formes fitteſt for our habilitie.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Commandeth he ſuch as can not make uſe of concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved formes, conſequently to read or hear them read?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> He willeth. 1. that they pray in ſet formes, and concur with them. 2. And if they can not read, they ſhould get ſome ſet formes perquier, by hearing them often repeated, by reading without reading. 3. And for that purpoſe miniſters ſhould read them: for the beſt memories, through cold and other deſeaſes will forget words unawares, and they ſay other words of the ſame ſenſe for them; yet it confoundeth weak memories, who are forced to forget the words, in whoſe place they hear new words repeated. A book is an artificiall memory ordained to help the weaknes of naturall memories, for this end God did writ his law on two tables, &amp; cauſed his prophets write the ſcriptures: Gods Spirit worketh holy motions in mens hearts at the hearing of his word read, and alſo of read prayers, which the enemies of read prayers confeſſe were dyted by Gods Spirit at the firſt conception; and what hindereth him to be ſtill effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all with his own work?</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is it not a ſhinting of prayers, if the weak ones uſe ſet formes only?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:23592:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is rather a ſtinting when the ſtrong ones uſe conceived formes only: they ſtint the forme though not the words: men ſtint their prayers when they uſe only a part, and not the full liberty which God hath granted in his word, when they are able to uſe the reſt alſo, which the weak ones cannot do. God hath given them liberty only to uſe a ſet form, for he hath not made them capable of any further, ſo that without miracle they can not conceive. 2. They who urge them to conceive becauſe others can conceive, they tempt God, as if they urged them to ſpeak all languages becauſe the apoſtles ſpake them: If God enlarge their gifts none hindereth them alſo to conceive. 3. Neither are they ſo ſtinred, but they have liberty to concur with conceived formes ſo far as they can. 4. But thou condemneſt thy ſelf in judging others who read prayers, when thou readeſt either pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or praiſe unto God at the ſinging of pſalmes, Gods Spirit worketh at the reading of both.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Do any deſpiſe ſet formes altogether?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, for ſome affirme that Gods ſpirit helpeth no mans infirmities, but at the firſt conception of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; but they fight againſt themſelves unawars, admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſundry prayers in a ſet forme. 1. They conclude the divine ſervice, ſaying the bleſſing in a ſet forme. 2. Their conceived prayers are ſet formes to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that concurre with them: It is a ſecond rehearſing of their prayers, for the people conceive them not. 3. They ſtint them to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> at the end of every pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: <hi>Amen</hi> is a ſhort ſumme of the prayer. 4. The preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers conclud their conceived prayers, with a ſet form like to this, <hi>To the Son, with the Father, and with the boly Spirit
<pb facs="tcp:23592:42"/>be glory, &amp;c.</hi> 5. At ſinging of pſalms, which is a ſet form of praiſe, they ſay alſo many prayers among them.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is it not ſluggiſhneſſe to uſe ſet formes, negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting varietie of meditations?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We neglect them not, for we conceive alſo. 2. If the uſe of ſet forms be ſluggiſhneſſe, then the contemners of ſe: forms are ſluggiſh, in uſing theſe ſet formes fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and the people which concur are ſluggiſh. 3. It is a greater ſluggiſhnes when men apply not ſet forms un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hearts, when their conſcience can not deny but they ſignifie their wants: they can not pray without no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veltie of words. Some were moved to pray with ſet forms, taking them to be new conceptions, becauſe they heard not theſe prayers before, but afterwards they loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed them alſo: They knew not the working of Gods Spirit, whereof they brag ſo much: they think Gods Spirit be like themſelves, delighting only in novelty of words, and abhorring his own words, which himſelf dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto Chriſtians before, ſo that he worketh no more by his own words, as they imagine; but they who grow in grace, deſpiſe not to uſe them alſo afterwards, as did Chriſt, and his deareſt Saints.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Can book prayers be ſteadable at our departing from this life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The laſt prayer that Chriſt ſaid upon the croſſe was a book prayer, written in the book of the pſalms, He rehearſeth it from the book of his memorie, <hi>Into thy bands I commit my Spirit, Pſal.</hi> 31) 2. Oftentimes at death God holdeth before men the book of his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, wherein all their ſenſes may read ſufficient mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for meditation and prayer. 3. A well formed pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for their preſent condition may be read to the great
<pb facs="tcp:23592:42"/>confort of diſtreſſed ſouls, who cannot read by themſelfs</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How know you if the words of ſet formes be dyted by Gods Spirit?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If they expreſſe things agreeable to Gods revealed will, in his word.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How know you if Gods Spirit teacheth us effectually, to uſe them rightly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Every man knoweth beſt what is in himſelf: if Gods Spirit work in his heart, hee prayeth expreſſing the words with faith, with fervent deſires and bumilitie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Gods glory, his own ſalvation, and the good of others: though his expreſſion be weak, his deſires may be fervent; no otherwiſe are conceived prayers known to be dyted and made uſefull by Gods Spirit: then as the reading of a ſupplication hindereth it not to be a ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation unto a King, and the reading of a pſalm hindereth it not to be a praiſe unto God, ſo the reading of prayers hindereth them not to be prayers, but it furthereth us being ready to ſupplie the defects of our memory, and it keepeth our mindes from wandring when our eyes and memories are fixed upon the ſame matter, for diverſe objects of the ſight oftimes perturbeth the memorie: and if we have not the words in our memorie, a well formed prayer in the book of things perpetually need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, will ſurniſh unto us matter and words for our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion: and it bringeth our wants to remembrance, Gods Spirit aſſiſteth all who uſe the lawfull meanes and confide not in their own ſtrength.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Do you match two or three read lines with Gods Spirit, as if they could inable us to pray?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Neither can two or three new conceptions
<pb facs="tcp:23592:43"/>inable us to pray. 2. By what ſpirit do you calumniat us as contemners of Gods Spirit, unto whom we never matched the Canonick Scriptures, much leſſe conceived and ſet forms; all which profit nothing, if Gods Spirit work not by them 3. In the pſalme fourth in miter. <hi>O Lord grant us thy countenance, thy favour and thy grace,</hi> all ſuch prayers of the pſalms in miter are paraphraſes of the text, as the read prayers are of ſome petitions of the Lords prayer: Thou by reading them at ſinging, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneſt thy ſelf in judging others who read prayers, which is more needfull then ſinging of pſalms in this life; if at the reading the words of prayer in the pſalms, thou prayeſt not in thy heart, if the words expreſſe thy wants, thou playeſt the hypocrite: and if thou pray, then thou readeſt a ſet form of prayer as well as of praiſe; for they are not new conceptions: You confeſſe that men ſpeak by the Spirit in their new conceptions: our ſet forms at the firſt expreſſion were new conceptions: then who bindeth the Spirit to the ſet forms of prayer in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, more then without miter? or who bindeth him to a read praiſe, more then to a read prayer? The Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableth us to both, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.18) 4. Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally all men abhor prayer more then ſinging of pſalms, becauſe of the melody in ſinging: if they pray without ſinging, they ſupplie the melody with novelty of words, which is admired by Pagans, as well as by Chriſtians: it proceedeth not from Gods Spirit in chriſtians, but from ſatan, and from their naturall part, to abhor any forme of worſhip, which was in requeſt with Chriſt and his dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſaints, and was dyted by Gods Spirit in his word: if Gods Spirit work not with him that readeth, becauſe the
<pb facs="tcp:23592:43"/>conceptions are not his: ſo is it with him him that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curreth, for the conceptions are not his, but if both apply the words to their hearts, the conceptions are theirs as truely as they were unto the firſt expreſſours: neither can any now living be the firſt expreſſour, for many have had the ſame conceptions before.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Reading ſeemeth more barnly, and therefore it is fitter for children then for aged men: it ſeemeth barnly, becauſe the words are few and often repeated, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Seeing Chriſt the ancient of dayes, and his Prophets and Apoſtles did read from the book of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, it becometh men, if they were older then <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſalem,</hi> and wiſer then <hi>Salomon,</hi> to read upon the artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall memorie of books: At Divine Service Chriſt did read on the book of <hi>Eſay, Luk.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. The apoſtles did read alſo on viſible bookes, for <hi>Paul</hi> had bookes and parchments. 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 4. Gods Spirit who was effectuall with Chriſt, reading a text of old concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; will alſo be effectuall with his members, reading old conceptions in any Divine Service. 2. The cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of read prayers is an indirect diſallowing of reading the Scriptures, except the Lords Prayer which expreſſeth all our wants, and that for the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which they uſe againſt read prayers, <hi>viz.</hi> They are read: They expreſſe not all our wants, Men know them before they read them, They are often repeated, They are not their conceptions who read them. 3. Thus thou diſalloweſt that aged men ſing pſalms, which is more barnelie then reading of prayers, for children delight more in muſick: But except we be humble like bairnes in ſubmitting
<pb facs="tcp:23592:44"/>our ſelves to the ſimplicitie of Gods word, we ſhall not enter into the kingdome of Heaven. 4. Reading and conceiving prayers, without feeling, is both bairnly and manly, for it is naturall to young and old, to pagans and Phariſaicall profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours; but if there be a ſenſe and feeling, Gods Spirit worketh it above nature. 5. If few conceptions ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> prayers bairn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then our ſet forms are more manly then almoſt all the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in Scripture of any form for we expreſſe mo conceptions in them. Thus our Novators will ſeem to have more of the working, and preſence of Gods Spirit, then all Gods Saints in Scripture, and out of Scripture, who follow not their errours, becauſe they have longer prayers. God grant that they devour not widows houſes, under pretence of long prayers, and that they think not to be heard by much ſpeaking, as Chriſt ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the Heathen, Matth. 6. Shall Chriſt and his Saints in Scripture be eſteemed leſſe zealous, leſſe religious, and of leſſe perfection, becauſe their prayers were ſhorter, and becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their prayers did not expreſſe all their wants.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Why hath Gods Spirit mixed prayers with the praiſing of God in the Pſalmes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That in our mirth and ſinging we ſhould not be exalted out of meaſure, but in the midſt of our mirth we ſhould remember our miſerie, in ſeeking iuccour and relief. 2. Becauſe the prayers include in themſelfs a confeſſion of his praiſe: for when we ſeek good things, it is an acknowledging that God is able and willing to give them: this is a great praiſe. 3. Chriſt in the Lords prayer did joine praiſe with prayer, to ſtir up our courage, in the aſſurance that God will hear us, when we ſay, <hi>For thine is the kingdome, power, and glory, &amp;c.</hi> And in the pſalms pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is joyned with praiſe, for the ſame end alſo; thus we pray in a cheerfull manner, and praiſe God in a modeſt gravitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Adde theſe following to the Chap. 5. Of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall and materiall praiſe in the pſalms.</head>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>WHat is divine praiſe formally?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. It is a ſerious and loving commemoration of any good thing that is in God, or from God, which is done to the
<pb facs="tcp:23592:44"/>ſetting foorth of his excellencie and worthineſſe: Thus if the words expreſſe directly his properties, and noble acts to be in him, or from him, whether in a proper or figurative ſpeach, it is a formall divine praiſe. It is acted two wayes; firſt, without melodie, and in proſe, as when Job ſaid, <hi>The Lord hath given, and the Lord hath taken, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord,</hi> Job 1. and David ſaid <hi>Let us fall into the hands of the LORD, for his mercies are great,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. Secondly, or with melodie vocall, or inſtrumentall. If it was vocall only, the Hebrews called it <hi>Shir,</hi> a ſong; if inſtruments were added to it, then it was called Mizmor, a pſalme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. What is divine praiſe materially, when this formalitie is not expreſſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. When the good things which procure praiſe unto God, or prove Him to be praiſe-worthie, are mentioned, not expreſſing any confeſſion that they belong unto God, as the firſt five verſes of the firſt pſalm prove by way of conſequent, that God is good, and bountifull, in that <hi>they are bleſſed, who ſit not with ſcorners, but meditate continually on Gods lavv, &amp;c.</hi> If God were not good and bountifull, they could not be bleſſed nor proſper; for as wicked tyrants afflict the godly rather than others, ſo would God do, if he were unmercifull and cruell. 2. When the wicked deeds of Doeg and Achitophell, and others are mentioned, it commendeth the long ſuffering patience of God, in that they lived on the earth a moment, &amp; his juſtice is more manifeſted in puniſhing them. 3. In the pſalmes 6.51. and 143. in their prayers, by way of conſequent God is acknowledged to bee Almighty, and mercifull, otherwiſe men would not ſeek ſuch things from him. 4. All formall praiſe conſiſteth in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed confeſſion and acknowledgement, that the good things are in God, or from God. The materiall praiſe hath not this confeſſion and acknowledgement expreſſed, but underſtood, and included in the words, and may be proven to be procured and merited, by the things mentioned in the words. 5. The materiall praiſe is as true and reall as the formall: as true praiſe is included in this prayer, Leave not my ſoul in hell; as when we ſay, Thou haſt not left, or doſt not, or ſhall not leave my ſoul in hell, by way of confeſſion, but the praiſe included in the prayer is not ſo conſpicuous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. Why is the book of divine praiſe called the book of the pſalmes, ſeeing many prayers are alſo in it?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:23592:45"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe theſe prayers are alſo divine praiſes materiallie, though not formallie, for divine praiſe is included in them. 2. Many works are named from the things in them, which are of greateſt moment, or many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in number: a book of <hi>Jeremy</hi> is called the <hi>Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> for it is full of mourning ſpeeches; yet divine praiſes and prayers are alſo in it: the books of the Kings have alſo hiſtories of ſome prieſts and prophets; the Lords prayer hath alſo ſome formall praiſe in it: <hi>viz. For thine is kingdome, power and glory, &amp;c.</hi> but mo formald petitions and prayers are in it, praiſe is included in them: in the firſt three, for things that concern Gods glory; in the laſt three, for things that concerns mans neceſſitie.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Can we in one ſentence and in the ſame words, both praiſe God, and pray unto him at once?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Many ſentences have formall praiſe, which include no prayer in them, as when we ſay, God is Almighty and Eternall, God dwelleth in heaven: Chriſt is the only begotten Son of God: he is God and Man in one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but no ſincere prayer wanteth divine praiſe inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in it: the formall prayers of the pſalmes have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall praiſes included in them, and ſo he that ſingeth the prayer doth alſo praiſe. 2. Two contraries in extreme degrees can not be in one ſubject, as they may be in their remitted degrees; prayer and praiſe are diverſe things, but not contrary: then as the Sun in one beame of light may ſend down both heat and illumination at once, ſo we may ſend up unto God prayer and praiſe in one ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, whether the prayer be formall and the praiſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall; as, <hi>O Lord rebuke me not in thine anger,</hi> for it redoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to Gods praiſe, that his reproof ſhould be feared:
<pb facs="tcp:23592:45"/>or the praiſe formall, and the prayer included in it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall: as a leper ſaid unto Chriſt, <hi>If thou wilt thou canſt make me clean:</hi> Item, <hi>A broken and contrite beart, O GOD, thou wilt not deſpiſe, Pſal.</hi> 51. Or whether a formall pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and a formall praiſe be together in one ſentence; as, <hi>Give ear, O ſheepbeard of Iſrael, thou that leadeſt Joſeph like a flock, Pſal.</hi> 80.) 3. Ioy and ſadneſſe are contrarie, Chriſtians may have them together in their remitted de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in this life; but in the next world the Elect ſhall have joy, and the reprobat ſadneſſe in their extreme de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. In this life if the joy of Chriſtians be greater then their ſadneſſe, they ſhould ſing formall or materiall praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or prayers: if their ſadneſſe be greater, they ſhould not ſing at all, as <hi>James</hi> ſayeth; but rather pray without ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, though praiſe be included in the prayer, they ſhould expreſſe leſſe mirth, when their ſadneſſe exceedeth their joy. Queſt. <hi>When we ſing a pſalme which hath prayers in it, we ſing to the praiſe of God, is this ſinging a formall, or materiall praiſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Both materiall and formall praiſe may be ſung to the praiſe of God. 2. In reſpect of the muſick our praiſe ſhould be formal keeping the right manner of the tune: and herein they tranſgreſſe, who interrupt muſical praiſe giving place to a reader, at the end of every line, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the line following. The pauſes uſed between lines is a comely ornament unto ſinging, and is as neceſſar to diſtinguiſh the lines, or principall parts of the tunes, as it is neceſſar that ſhorter pauſes ſhould divide every note from another: without diſtinctions and pauſes all the tune ſhould be but one note: Muſick without number and diviſion is not muſick: but muſicall praiſe is defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:23592:46"/>by a non muſical interruption of reading, and Gods ordinance ordeined to chear up men for divine praiſe, is deformed and rent, and ſo it abaiteth chearfulneſſe, they do evill that good may come of it, chooſing a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed muſicall praiſe, when they may have a rightly formed praiſe, They do it, that ignorant people may ſing with them. But humane will-worſhip can not take a good effect, for Gods Spirit never taught it; Therefore in ſtead of praiſe, they abuſe Gods name, becauſe they ſing oftimes many lines, not knowing what they ſay of God, even when the ſentence is ended. Their blind zeal do not read ſentences of prayer, that the ignorant may learn to pray which is more needfull in this life: It were better to ſing perquier but one verſe of a pſalme all our lifetime, then to deforme Gods worſhip, thus ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the pſalms. Some uſe this deformitie, becauſe nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardneſſe hindereth them to buy a number of pſalme books, and ſlugiſhneſſe hindreth them to teach their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticks to read. 3. Where there are two, or four, or ſix or mo lines in a ſentence, before the laſt line be heard, the ignorant know not what they have ſung, and ſo they play the hypocrit and abuſe Gods name, ſeeming to praiſe GOD when they know not what they ſay of God, and when the laſt line is read, many know not the ſenſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have forgotten what was ſung, and ſo ſtill they abuſe Gods name: And ſuch as know the ſenſe alſo abuſe Gods name, for they have but ſung the laſt line only with underſtanding: It is a none ſenſe to ſing a part and not the whole fentence with underſtanding; And though ſome have the pſalme in their memorie, yet they deforme Gods worſhip, interrupting it with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.
<pb facs="tcp:23592:46"/>When ignorant papiſts pray in Latine, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they ſay, it is as true Divine worſhip as when we ſing words of praiſe in our own language, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what we ſay. If any ſing reading on a book, not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king heed what he ſaith, it is but his own fault, and hee may amend it at other times, but when a multitude is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by a law or cuſtom to do it, this is more antichriſtian like; the ignorant might praiſe God in their hearts with a hundreth fold more true devotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; with underſtanding if only the pſalme were read to them in proſe or in verſe. But the pride of the obſtinat will not amend, thogh they know their errours. In reſpect of the tranſcendent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of all the pſalms, the praiſe of every pſalm may be called formall, for every pſalm hath ſome formall praiſe in it, even the penitentiall pſalms, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.8, 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.16, 17) 4. Materiall praiſe in ſinging may be made formall, by adding to it, and concluding it with a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of formall praiſe, as <hi>Glory to the Father, and to the Son &amp;c,</hi> importing, that not only the glory of all things, but particularly of the things mentioned in the words preſently ſung; belongeth to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant get theſe words, with the laſt verſe of the pſalm 28. <hi>viz. Thy people and thine heritage, &amp;c.</hi> they may ſing them orderly, albeit they ſing no more with the reſt at all occaſions; for theſe words of prayer and praiſe are as ſubſtantiall and plain, as any words in the book of the the pſalms. 5. When men ſing words which have no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall confeſſion, they may make the praiſe formall in their hearts, if they conſider and acknowledge what work God hath in the things mentioned by theſe words. 6. When formall prayers, and other ſpeaches are equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent
<pb facs="tcp:23592:47"/>to formall praiſes, they may alſo bee called for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall praiſes.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How are they equivalent to formall praiſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If a formall praiſe be added to a formall pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, in the ſame ſentence, as in the third petition of the Lords prayer, <hi>Thy will be done in earth &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.1. <hi>Have mercy on me, O God, according to thy loving kindneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> 2. If in the prayer Gods name be expreſſed, with epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thites of praiſe, as, <hi>Give ear O ſheepheard of Iſrael Pſal.</hi> 80) 3. If the matter and purpoſe of the prayer concerne the manifeſting of GODS glory, in expreſſe words, as in the firſt two petitions of the Lords prayer. <hi>In Pſal.</hi> 115, <hi>Not unto us O Lord, but unto thy name give the glory:</hi> The third petition of the Lords prayer is a formall praiſe, both in this reſpect, and in the reſpect forſaid. 4. Speach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es that are not formall praiſes by expreſſed confeſſion, if they attribute unto God honourable and divine things, by inſinuation, they are formall praiſes by inſinuation, as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>Serve the Lord with fear and rejoice in trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling,</hi> for it is a direct formall praiſe that God ſhould be ſerved and feared.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Who are actors of Gods praiſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The elect men and angels act his formall praiſes, when they conſider his excellent works, and the good things in them, and the good things of God mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in his word, and works, And they aſcribe all the honour and glory thereof unto God, by confeſſing him to be the Author, Conſerver and Ruler of all, more Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then all, void of all imperfections, and wants that are in all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They act his materiall praiſe alſo, in that themſelves are the excellent works of God, a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:23592:47"/>of great praiſe; and therefore they ſhould take notiſe of themſelves, to be ſtirred up to praiſe God formally, as they are alwayes his praiſe materially. 2. All other creatures act only his materiall praiſes, that is, They are a matter of his praiſe, in that they ſhow forth in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves admirable effects of his power, wiſdome, love, bountifulneſſe, juſtice and holineſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which things prove &amp; procure moſt great praiſe and glory, And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the pſalme 148. all creatures are exhorted to praiſe God, that is, They ſhould ſhow forth the excellent things that God placed in them, that the great creator of all may be taken notiſe of thereby and praiſed. The pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt ſpeaketh to dumb creaturs who can not make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, but in that God inableth them to hold out &amp; ſhow to the world his excellent gifts, it is in ſtead of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, for it is a materiall praiſing of God. And alſo his ſpeach to creatures void of underſtanding provoketh men to take notiſe of Gods gifts in the creatures, to be ſtirred up to praiſe God formallie, leſt they prove worſe then the creatures.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Our Pſalms in meeter, are they a tranſlation, or a paraphraſe of the Hebrew text? You call them paraphraſes, as the ſet forms of prayer are of the Lords prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The miter ſhoweth them to be paraphraſes, for it hath the meaning of the text in mo words then a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation requireth. 2. When tranſlators adde mo words; then the juſt interpretation requireth, it is, becauſe the meaning of the text can not otherwiſe be underſtood, and yet the text that hath theſe words added, if with theſe words all be conſidered, as parts of one ſentence, they are a ſhort paraphraſe, becauſe more then the text
<pb facs="tcp:23592:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>is added to explicat the text: But when all the words or ſentences of the book are explicat and illuſtrat by other words, there the whole work is a paraphraſe. 3. The moſt learned Latine Poets call their pſalms turned mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer a paraphraſe; <hi>Buchanan</hi> calleth his pſalms <hi>Paraphraſis Poetica,</hi> becauſe ſometimes ſentences, figurative ſpeaches, and other illuſtrations, and words are added to the text: ſometimes the words of the text are turned into other words, and ſentences of the ſame ſenſe: theſe things are done in the whole work, that the Poet may have chooſe of words to make the miter agree with the text: ſo is it with our pſalms in miter, for no Scriptures can bee turned into miter by a naked tranſlation.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>If our pſalms in miter be a paraphraſe, then we may make paraphraſes of all the Scripturs, and ſo read them publictly.</hi> A. That is not needful, for many ſcripturs are underſtood at the reading without a paraphraſe. 2. If our pſalms in meeter were only the tranſlated text, then Preachers ſhould make ſermons on them, and readers ſhould read them publictly, as they do other ſcripturs, &amp; the verſes in miter cited to prove matters of divine verity. 3. It were not hurtfull, but profitable for the hearers, ſometimes to read paraphraſes of all ſcriptures; but this is ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plied by preaching, catechiſing, &amp; by the plainnes of many ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturs, at the reading then theſe paraphraſes are not ſo needfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt, Seeing the tranſlators of other Scripturs adde ſome vvords to the text, vvhy may not the tranſlations be called paraphraſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> If the whole ſcripturs had illuſtrations, &amp; other helps forſaid, in every ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence as the book of the pſalms hath, then might it be ſo called, but ſuch helps are few, &amp; ſeldom fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in other ſcripturs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Adde theſe following to the chap. 6. <hi>viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIve ſome example in the book of the Pſalms, where the vvhole ſentence Gloris to the Father, and to the Son, &amp;c. is ſaid in ſubstance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. In Pſal. 110.1. The Lord ſaid to my Lord, &amp;c. that
<pb facs="tcp:23592:48"/>is, The Father ſaid to the Son, ſit thou at my right hand, &amp;c. and verſ. 2. the holy Ghoſt is called The rod of thy ſtrength: He is a golden ſcepter, holden out to comfort the godly, but an yron rod to bruiſe the wicked; thus glory is given to all the three perſons, the Father is glorified, in ſubduing the enemies of Chriſt; the Son is glorified, in ſitting at the right hand of God, and that his enemies ſhall be his footſtool; the holy Ghoſt is glorified, in that he is the effectuall rod of Gods power, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the mids of Chriſts enemies, and ſubduing them: and in verſe 4. the Eternitie of the three perſons is expreſſed, in that the Lord made Chriſt a Prieſt for ever, without beginning, and without ending, becauſe He is after the order of Melchiſedeck, Heb. 7. He can not be a prieſt for ever, except God his Father continue for ever; for none can be a prieſt, without a God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom he muſt offer ſacrifice, and with whom he muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceed for people: the holy Ghoſt muſt alſo continue for ever; for if the anoynting whereby Chriſt is effectuall ſhall ceaſe at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time, then Chriſt could no longer remain a prieſt, nor doe that office. So in this pſalm God is glorified according to the full ſentence wherewith we conclude our pſalmes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. Pope Damaſus cauſed firſt that ſentence be ſung in Gods Kirk, ſhould we not reiect it, becauſe papiſts firſt practiſed it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. Shall no man make uſe of cities, tents, harps, and muſicall inſtruments, becauſe curſed Cain builded the firſt city, and his children invented the reſt? Balaam the falſe prophet fiſt ſaid, <hi>Let me die the death of the righteous.</hi> Palladius ſent from pope Celeſtine, brought the goſpel firſt into Scotland; and one Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine ſent from pope Gregorie, brought it into England, when popiſh ſuperſtition was greater then in the dayes of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſus, who lived in the 400 year, Palladius in the 500. and this Auguſtine in the 600 year of Chriſt. The builders of Babel firſt ſpake all languages, ſhall wee therefore abſteene from all theſe things? 2. Therefore let us embrace the good things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to Gods word, which they made uſe of, but caſt away the infidelitie of Balaam, the vain confidence of the builders of Babel, the ſuperſtition of papiſts, who uſed this ſentence at the maſſe, and at the end of every pſalm read or ſung. 3. Pope Damaſus ſaid not firſt the ſubſtance of that ſentence, neither
<pb facs="tcp:23592:49"/>uſed he it firſt in muſicall praiſe; the ſubſtance of it was ſaid in Revel. 4.8. and it was ſung when the pſalm 100. was firſt ſung; and other paſſages of the pſames have the ſentence included in them, as the pſalm 45. verſ. 7. pſalm 2. and ſalm 136.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt. Is it comely at one exerciſe of divine praiſe, to ſing parts of diverſe pſalmes together, as if they were parts of one pſalm or ſong, and that in publict meetings?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Gods Spirit approveth it by the like practiſe, in 1 Chron. 16 7. When David gave a pſalm to thank the Dord, into the hands of Aſaph and his brethren: this ſong or pſalm was made up thus, to wit, from the verſe eight of the chapter, unto the end of the verſe 23. are written fifteene verſes of the pſalme 105. and from the 23 verſe, unto the end of the verſe 33. are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the words of the whole pſalme 96. and in the verſe 34. is the firſt verſe of the pſalm 107. all is one ſong. Item the firſt five verſes of the pſal 108. are the laſt five verſes of the pſal 57. and the reſt of the pſal. 108. are the laſt eight verſ. of the pſal. 60.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quest. Is it not good to practiſe ſome of theſe erroneous novations, for eſchew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſhiſme, and for keeping of union and conformitie with ſome religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who in great Zeal defend them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Zeal in defending error is not a godly but a blind zeal; it is thus known, in that they defend theſe errors as carefully as they do the cleareſt principals of divine veritie, and they perſecute ſuch as embrace them not, as if they were hereticks. 2. Would thou keep union with them in their errours, rather than with Chriſt and his apoſtles, who were immediatly taught by Gods Spirit in divine veritie, which admitteth not ſuch novations. By ſo doing, you eſchew not, but you entertaine a moſt dangerous ſchiſme, dividing your ſelves from the puritie of the moſt loyal and infallible preachers of the truth. 3. If for to make you ſtrong with humane friendſhip you ſo deſpiſe Gods truth, that you make errors equall unto it, profeſſing both together, as if they were both but one truth, then it will be a juſt reward, if God ſuffer you to fall by degrees into palpable antichriſtian darkneſſe and if God kindle unquenchable hatred and diſcord, between you and your affected ſocietie, wo ſhall be to him that maketh fleſh his arme. Jerem. 17.5.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:23592:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
